<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian prudence, or, Directions for the guidance and conduct of our selves in the case of judging one another being several discourses on Math. 7, 1 / by G. Bright.</title>
            <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 234 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 114 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29499</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4671</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30249</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11275758</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11275758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47246</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29499)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47246)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1456:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian prudence, or, Directions for the guidance and conduct of our selves in the case of judging one another being several discourses on Math. 7, 1 / by G. Bright.</title>
                  <author>G. B. (George Bright), d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 199 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Matt. Wotton ... and G. Conyers ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [22].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew VII, 1 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Prudence,</hi> OR, <hi>Directions</hi> FOR THE Guidance and Conduct of our Selves, In the Caſe of Judging one another.</p>
            <p>Being ſeveral Diſcourſes on</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATTH. 7. 1.</bibl> Judge not, that you be not judged.</q>
            <p>By <hi>G. Bright,</hi> late Dean of St. <hi>Aſaph,</hi> Rector of <hi>Loughborough,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Matt. Wotton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Daggers</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and <hi>G. Conyers,</hi> at the <hi>Ring</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> Price <hi>1s. 6d.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>Cum Charitate &amp; pruden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
                  <p>London Printed for Iohn Wright</p>
                  <byline>P Holmes ſclp</byline>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:3"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Good Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe Reaſon in very ſhort why this ſmall Treatiſe is Publiſhed is, becauſe it was judged, that there would likely ſome more Good come of it than of not doing it, and this again becauſe the Matter therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained was thought true, and in ſome conſiderable degree uſeful and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and not yet either ſo particularly, or in ſuch Method and Manner diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any other as to render this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſuperfluous.</p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe is but too little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded eſpecially in Practical Matters, where Men attending principally to the Practice of them, do leſs mind the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and exact Truth, and therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are not (as commonly they are) too unlimitedly and generally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Beſides Men commonly receive Practical things and what is taught con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Duty with more general
<pb facs="tcp:47246:4"/> Veneration, which makes them more eaſily and preſently to attribute to them the perfection of Truth, or to judg them true. Men are apt too to ſuſpect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of ſome unwillingneſs to do, and conſequently to know their duty, when they queſtion and examine whether it be truly ſo or no; and that this ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and doubting proceeds from thence, which indeed is too often true, whence it comes to paſs that Men are generally more careleſs and ſecure concerning the truth of theſe Matters when they deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, and many hurtful miſtakes are conveyed with ſome profitable truths.</p>
            <p>As for the profitableneſs of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, and what is diſcourſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, I know it will be variouſly judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to Mens various inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or informations. Men judg things profitable, either becauſe they will, it pleaſeth them to judg ſo, or becauſe they ſee and perceive them to be ſo; that is becauſe they perceive and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the good effects thereof, the one commonly is called the Judgment
<pb facs="tcp:47246:4"/> of affection (becauſe our inclinations are uſually from Affection) the other the judgment of Reaſon; both may be in ſeveral, nay in the ſame Men various enough. The firſt is the moſt inconſtant and diverſe, but the ſecond is ſo too ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Mens various informations or apprehenſions from Reaſon or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; one Man may have obſerved and remembred many excellent effects or uſes of any certain thing, another ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few, or none, or bad ones only, whence one judgeth it very profitable, another very little ſo, or not at all, or bad and hurtful, and yet both may judg pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently and truly, if it be only of what appears to them: I leave every one free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their own Reaſon and Obſervation in this particular, only I ſuggeſt that they would not exclude their future in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, that they would not judg on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to what they have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but alſo according to what they may hereafter obſerve themſelves, or learn from others. The miſcarriages in judging one another are ſo univerſal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the common ſort of Chriſtians,
<pb facs="tcp:47246:5"/> and ſo frequent and little regarded even in wiſer and better diſpoſed, and yet ſo very miſchievous, as may be partly underſtood from one part of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, that it is to be preſumed the miſchievous effects thereof have not been hitherto ſo much taken notice of and reſented, as they ſeem to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in compare with other Matters. We ſee Men every day eagerly and fiercely and even to Perſecution to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend concerning the uſefulneſs and truth of their knowledg and judgment in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Opinions Religious, Secular, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane, which would put ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowing but unprejudiced Men to much ſtudy to find out any good uſe or effect thereof, more than oft-times the pleaſure of meer knowing ſome-what though very uſeleſs, confuſedly, or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceited ſome great matter by them; when in the mean time they are utterly careleſs of their knowledg and judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one another, whence it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt they are preſently affected with mutual eſteem and love, or with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and hatred, are Friends or Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,
<pb facs="tcp:47246:5"/> and conſequently effectually diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be negligent of at leaſt, or to do good or miſchief to one another, and conſequently to hinder or help what they are good for in the World, and who knows where the Good or Evil may ſtop? I hope it will not be the leſs uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and truly valuable for being that which is truly Moral Knowledg: For that being only the knowledg of our Manners, that is, the habitual inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Wills, Choices, and active Faculties, what ſhould be perpetually their ultimate Object or their End, which can be but one, <hi>viz.</hi> The great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perfection and happineſs of the whole Univerſe known to us taking in God himſelf, what the intermediate ones or means; in what degree they are to be proportioned. The Knowledg of the one true and right end and juſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of all our habitual Inclinations and Actions, I ſay, Moral Knowledg being this, it is manifeſt there is no other Knowledge we are capable of compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for its good uſe and effect, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently much to be valued, ſeparated
<pb facs="tcp:47246:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47246:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47246:7"/> there-from, or conſidered not ſubſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or inſtrumental thereto.</p>
            <p>For by it alone we are directed to the obtainment of that perfection, by which we tend to do any good to others, or which keeps from doing any harm, the fruit or good effect of other Knowledg conſidered alone is chiefly the pleaſure and delight immediately ariſing to the Mind, and is confined within our ſelves. Good Morality in this ſenſe is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perfection our Natures are capable of, being nothing but the univerſal right determination of our Wills and Choices to the beſt and moſt excellent end, <hi>viz.</hi> The greateſt Perfection and Happineſs of the whole Univerſe, taking in God himſelf: It is nothing but Univerſal Goodneſs, it tends to an infinite good without our ſelves, and therefore no wonder that the poſſeſſion and exerciſe of it in ſincerity and vigour fills the Soul with the greateſt delight and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction. All other things in the World may be uſed well or ill, and ſeem to be equally capable of both, and therefore indifferent; this only cannot be the
<pb facs="tcp:47246:7"/> cauſe of any thing but good in the World, nor can it be conceived that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing elſe ſhould render us capable of reward from God, that is, of any Happineſs or Perfection, but at leaſt a Will to do all the Good with it that it is uſable for. For why ſhould we have either, if we do no Good, or do Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief therewith? But if this Morali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be the moſt excellent thing we are capable of: Then ſure is its Knowledg.</p>
            <p>Some have valued and prized Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg by other Characters than Uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and good Effects; ſuch as is its be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Revelation or inſpired: And therefore have thought every Truth and the leaſt revealed to be of greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment or worth more than the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt known by reaſon or natural Light, eſpecially if not revealed too; not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending that the Reaſon of Revelation is not only the utility of a truth (though there is always ſufficient) but the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of its being otherwiſe known.</p>
            <p>Much more might have been ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſo conſiderable a Matter: But this is enough if not too much in this place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:8"/>
            <p>Laſtly, As for this Diſcourſe's not being ſuperfluous, I ſhould be glad to be miſtaken, and that this Argument hath been ſo Handled and Treated of alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as to render this uſeleſs.</p>
            <p>I ſhall give thee no further trouble (Good Reader) but only deſire that thou wouldſt read this Treatiſe (if thou thinkeſt fit to read at all) with the ſame deſign it was Compoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> Of Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance and Conduct of our ſelves in this particular, and conſequently that it might contribute ſome-thing to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of univerſal Charity, Juſtice, and Wiſdom in the World.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:8"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <item>§. I. <hi>THe ſeveral ſenſes of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to Judg.</hi> p. 7, 8.</item>
               <item>§ II. <hi>That in the general ſenſe of the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to Judg, two parts may be obſerved, 1. The inward action of Mind. 2. The ſignification of the Action.</hi> p. 11, 12.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>What Judgments may be thought forbidden by our Saviour both Principally and Secondarily, or Occaſionally, are reckoned up, which are ſix.</hi> p. 13, 14.</item>
               <item>§. I. <hi>The firſt prohibited Judgment, too great a proneneſs to paſs our Judgments concerning Perſons in any reſpect at all.</hi> p. 15.</item>
               <item>§. II. <hi>The ſecond is too great a proneneſs to paſs judgment on the worſt ſide.</hi> p. 19, 20.</item>
               <item>§. III. <hi>The third is raſh Judgment, without any reaſon or without ſufficient reaſon.</hi> p. 23, 24, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>§. IV. <hi>The fourth is falſe Judgment.</hi> p. 29.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:47246:9"/>
               <item>§. V. <hi>The fifth thing forbidden is too great a proneneſs to declare and ſignifie our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> p. 34.</item>
               <item>§. VI. <hi>The ſixth and principal is the undue end of Judging,</hi> viz. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltimately to pleaſe ones ſelf, (Selfiſhneſs, Self-love) and this by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Hatred, Pride, Affectation of Superiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Revenge, Envy, Flattery, by Anger, Fear, Buſie-bodineſs, Curioſity.</hi> p. 37, 38.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. III. What Judgments are not forbidden.</head>
               <item>§. I. 1. <hi>In general not a Judging out of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> p. 39.</item>
               <item>§. II. 2. <hi>In general not when there are and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more good Effects thereof than of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</hi> p. 40.</item>
               <item>§. III. 3. <hi>Many particular Caſes are inſtanced in for example to our Prudence, in which it is not prohibited in general to obſerve and paſs Judgment concerning others Qualities and Actions.</hi> p. 42, 43.</item>
               <item>§. IV. 4. <hi>It is not prohibited univerſally to paſs Judgment on the worſt ſide.</hi> p. 45.</item>
               <item>§. V. 5. <hi>It is not univerſally forbidden to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our Judgment and that on the worſt ſide.</hi> p. 46.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:47246:9"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. Contains ſome Cauſes of theſe forbidden Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</head>
               <item>§. I. <hi>The Cauſes of too much proneneſs to Judg in general, of which the firſt Idleneſs.</hi> p. 49.</item>
               <item>§. II. <hi>The ſecond love of Activity, of doing ſomewhat.</hi> p 52.</item>
               <item>§. III. <hi>The third is Curioſity or of knowing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what.</hi> p. 54.</item>
               <item>§. IV. <hi>The fourth a Self-pleaſing in our Ability or reputed Ability to judg.</hi> p. 56.</item>
               <item>§. V. <hi>Cauſes of too great proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide, of which the firſt is meer Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</hi> p. 57.</item>
               <item>§. VI. <hi>The ſecond ill diſpoſitions of Will, as 1. Hatred. 2. Revenge. 3. Pride. 4. More particularly Affectation of Superiority in any thing. 5. Envy. 6. Contempt. 7. Flattery.</hi> p. 59.</item>
               <item>§. VII. <hi>That the Cauſes of raſh Judgment are the ſame with thoſe of the two former.</hi> p. 68.</item>
               <item>§. VIII. <hi>That the Cauſes of falſe Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Perſons are defect in our underſtanding, in our Will.</hi> p. 69.</item>
               <item>§. IX. <hi>The firſt Cauſe reducible to one of thoſe two is Ignorance.</hi> p. 70.</item>
               <item>§. X. <hi>The ſecond an Opinion or Judgment too unlimited, that all Men are like our ſelves: Some inſtances hereof: This extended to God
<pb facs="tcp:47246:10"/> himſelf; that it hath been the Cauſe of making God in Humane Shape, and that the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting God or any thing in him by Humane Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe is likewiſe the Cauſe of ſuch an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion concerning God.</hi> p. 76, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>§. XI. <hi>The th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd is too general a belief of Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony or Report.</hi> p. 85.</item>
               <item>§. XII. <hi>The fourth Cauſe is an obſerving only what is good or what is bad in a Perſon, and not obſerving both.</hi> p. 88.</item>
               <item>§. XIII. <hi>A fifth is a want of a prevalent love of Truth.</hi> p. 92, 93.</item>
               <item>§. XIV. <hi>A ſixth is our Paſſions, the inſtances thereof. That Paſſions determine our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments three ways among others. 1. By bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mind only thoſe things which are true indeed, but ſerve to maintain or encreaſe them; but keeping out thoſe which tend to abate them, ſo that they never appear. 2. By thruſting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Minds more than is true of that which maintains them. 3. By thruſting out thoſe things which may be ſuggeſted and true, but yet ſerve to extinguiſh them; or by cauſing a Man not to attend thereto, or the Evidence that is in them; or by confounding the atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or perception on purpoſe that it might not ſee the moſt neceſſary truth which it cannot deny if it did ſee.</hi> p. 97, 98, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>§. 15. <hi>A ſeventh Cauſe of falſe Judgment ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the good or bad part is all Appetites whatſoever, beſides thoſe of Truth and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Juſtice, of which one more uſeful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47246:10"/> p. 106.</item>
               <item>§. 16. <hi>The Cauſes of too great a proneneſs to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our Judgments much the ſame with what have been mentioned,</hi> viz. <hi>Idleneſs, Self-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by Activity, Curioſity, Conceit of abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and ſufficiency to judg, by fancied Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there for, by Hatred, Revenge, Pride, Affectation of Superiority, Envy, Contempt, Anger, Flattery.</hi> p. 110.</item>
               <item>§. 17. <hi>The Cauſes of the laſt prohibited Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of ſuch bad Principles as are above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, the Corruption of our Natures impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by Cuſtome, and wilful ill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage of our ſelves.</hi> p. 111.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. V. Treats of the miſchievous Conſequences or Effects of theſe prohibited Judgments.</head>
               <item>§. I. <hi>The ill Effects of too great a proneneſs to judg others in general are,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>1. <hi>Too great a neglect of our own Affairs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and principally our Manners, in which we are prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to employ our ſelves. For, 1. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſo well know that in another Man concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which we paſs judgment, as what is in our ſelves. And, 2. We can make more certain effectual uſe of our Judgment and Obſervation of our ſelves.</hi> p. 112, 113, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A 2d. ill Effect of too great proneneſs to judg in general, is an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of anothers right,
<pb facs="tcp:47246:11"/> or Tyranny.</hi> p. 118, 119:</item>
               <item>§. II. <hi>The ill Conſequences of too great proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide are, 1. Falſe Judgment. 2. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Contempt, 3. oft-times unjuſt Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in others of the Judgment coming from the worſt Principles, whence 4. Contempt, Hatred, Revenge in the Perſons judged againſt the Perſon judging.</hi> p. 122, 123.</item>
               <item>§. III. <hi>The ill Conſequences of raſh Judgment are, 1. The uſage of a Mans ſelf thereto. 2. The rendring a Man's Teſtimony inconſiderable. 3. It is occaſion to Men of Hatred, Contempt, Anger,</hi> &amp;c. p. 125.</item>
               <item>§. IV. <hi>The ill Conſequences of falſe Judgment are, 1. A Man's own Diſcredit. 2. The ill diſtribution of the Good or Evil that is in a Man's power to beſtow or inflict.</hi> p. 126.</item>
               <item>§. V. <hi>The ill Conſequences of too great a prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to declare ones Judgment are, 1. It ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders a Man contemptible. 2. It draws others from their Buſineſs. 3. Mutual Suſpicions, Animoſities, Envyings, Contempts or fooliſh Admiration and Eſteem, vain Truſt and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</hi> p. 127.</item>
               <item>§. VI. <hi>The ill Conſequences of judging out of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Revenge, Pride, Affectation of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, Envy, Anger, Contempt, Flattery,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are, 1. The increaſe of thoſe Paſſions with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir ill Principles in our ſelves and others, which are the moſt deteſtable things, 2. It ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth to the Hatred, Anger, Revenge, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of others. 3. The Perſons who are thus
<pb facs="tcp:47246:11"/> judged by us, judging us again untruly on the worſt ſide out of Revenge.</hi> p. 133.</item>
               <item>§. VII. <hi>The contrary of all theſe miſchievous Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Conſequences put together and briefly counted.</hi> p. 138.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VI. Contains ſome Remedies to prevent thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Judgments. Of which the</head>
               <item>§. I. 1. <hi>And one of the moſt general is to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and attend to the miſchievous Conſequences thereof, as alſo their Cauſes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The one to make us willing, the other able to abſtain there-from. Thoſe more affectionately Repreſented, and theſe Exhorted againſt.</hi> p. 146.</item>
               <item>§. II. <hi>A ſecond Remedy is to poſseſs our hearts with an univerſal Charity and Benignity to all.</hi> p. 155.</item>
               <item>§. III. 3. <hi>Is to rivet ſoundly in our Minds the love of Truth.</hi> p. 156.</item>
               <item>§. IV. 4. <hi>More particularly ask thy ſelf again and again, whether thou art ſure thy Judgment be true.</hi> p. 157.</item>
               <item>§. V. 5. <hi>Ask thy ſelf whether thou wouldſt not have true what thou judgeſt.</hi> p. 160.</item>
               <item>§. VI. 6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe thy ſelf much to dwell at Home.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
               <item>§. VII. 7. <hi>Have a ſpecial care of all Paſſions that they do not precede but follow thy Reaſon, and when they do this, that they do not blind or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
<pb facs="tcp:47246:12"/> it.</hi> p. 162.</item>
               <item>§. VIII. 8. <hi>More particularly be ſparing in, or refrain altogether from judging a Perſon thou art inclined to hate or be angry with, or more expreſly then ſet thy ſelf to ſhake off all Preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices, of which more, and more properly in the Rules to follow.</hi> p. 164.</item>
               <item>§. IX. 9. <hi>Diſcourſe more of Things than Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. VII. Some few Rules to be obſerved in our Judging generally and for the moſt part.</head>
               <item>§. I. <hi>Paſs and declare all thy Judgments out of Charity. This Charity how meant. The ſigns of this Charity to others in judging. 1. More readineſs to judg on the good ſide than on the bad. 2. An excuſing others, and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all we can juſtly for them. 3. Frequent judging our ſelves. 4. Calmneſs and Modeſty.</hi> p. 164.</item>
               <item>§. II. <hi>A ſecond Rule briefly mention'd is to judg truly.</hi> p. 173.</item>
               <item>§. III. <hi>A third, Have a care of all Paſſions, but eſpecially of Anger before Judgment.</hi> p. ibid.</item>
               <item>§. IV. <hi>A fourth, Declare not thy Judgment, when thou thy ſelf art guilty, of which the Reaſons.</hi> p. 175.</item>
               <item>§. V. <hi>A fifth, If thou judgeſt when guilty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve
<pb facs="tcp:47246:12"/> to be innocent for the future, and firſt condemn thy ſelf, of which the Reaſons, 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe every one ought to love himſelf as well as his Neighbour in all Circumſtances alike, 2. It is an excellent Example in a thing very rare, and yet extraordinary uſeful. 3. Ones own Judgment concerning others is thereby rendred more effectual. 4. Every one knoweth more certainly the truth of his Judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf. 5. Men's Care and Zeal will be here more certainly employed with ſucceſs.</hi> p. 177.</item>
               <item>§. VI. <hi>A ſixth, That it is more ſafe generally not to declare thy Judgment than to do it, of which one Reaſon.</hi> p. 179.</item>
               <item>§. VII. <hi>A ſeventh, Be more cautious in paſſing or declaring thy Judgment in theſe following Caſes, 1. Concerning thy Superiours. 2. Thy Friends, 3. Thy Enemy. 4. A Perſon ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally innocent and well-diſpoſed, but once or rarely overtaken. 5. Wrathful and Baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Perſons. 6. Before much Company. 7. Before Enemies. Of all theſe their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Reaſons.</hi> p. 180.</item>
               <item>§. VIII. <hi>An eighth is, Be inclin'd rather to defer thy Judgment till thou art deſired. Some Reaſons hereof.</hi> p. 190.</item>
               <item>§. IX. <hi>A ninth, Is more freely and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to paſs or declare Judgment concerning one to another, when thou ſeeſt a Perſon concern'd, defective in his Ability or Care for himſelf.
<pb facs="tcp:47246:13"/> Followed with ſome Reaſons, theſe Rules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recounted briefly.</hi> p. 192.</item>
               <item>§. 10. <hi>An Exhortation to the exerciſe of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Prudence in this ſo conſiderable a part of our Converſation, the Scope and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the whole Treatiſe.</hi> p. ult.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47246:14"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pag.</cell>
                     <cell>Line</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>For</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Read</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>Fooliſhly out of, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>Fooliſhly, out of &amp;c. and a little readineſs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>And readineſs,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>Dele and.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>Contrary to the, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>contrary to it, the.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>Judgment: This raſh</cell>
                     <cell>Judgment. This &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                     <cell>Principally moreover,</cell>
                     <cell>Principally: Moreo. are.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>Thoſe out of, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>Thoſe. Out of, &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>There, for, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>Therefor,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                     <cell>Our ſelves ſo to do;</cell>
                     <cell>Our ſelves, ſo to do;</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>Pleaſures,</cell>
                     <cell>Pleaſure.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>It is ſo: In, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>It is ſo. In, &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>To be an excellent,</cell>
                     <cell>To be in an excellent.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                     <cell>(For Chriſt)</cell>
                     <cell>(For Example.)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>Looks,</cell>
                     <cell>Books.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8</cell>
                     <cell>Encreaſed,</cell>
                     <cell>Increaſed.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>(which obtains in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate things but principally in &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>(which may be to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate things, but principally to, &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>99</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                     <cell>Many or all, perhaps</cell>
                     <cell>Many or all perhaps,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>104</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>By bringing into our Minds not only what</cell>
                     <cell>Not only bringing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our minds what.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>106</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                     <cell>And favour; nay, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>And favour. Nay</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>117</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                     <cell>More then in thine, is,</cell>
                     <cell>More in thine, &amp;c. are.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>122</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>124</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>129</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                     <cell>To bad, &amp;c.</cell>
                     <cell>Too bad, &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>ib.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                     <cell>Too be, etc.</cell>
                     <cell>To be, &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>135</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                     <cell>More ore leſs,</cell>
                     <cell>More or leſs.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>146</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>when we judg to do,</cell>
                     <cell>when we judg, to do.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>147</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>There-from. The</cell>
                     <cell>There-from, the &amp;c.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>153</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>Inſtruction: Hardly.</cell>
                     <cell>Inſtruction. Hardly.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47246:14"/>
            <head>A TREATISE CONCERNING <hi>Iudging one another.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Mat. 7. 1.</bibl>
                  <q>Judg not that you be not Judged.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>A Very good Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of any Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Subject of Diſcourſe, is its Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of very Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and Hurtful Effects and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences: Such is this of Mens paſſing Judgment concerning other Mens Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47246:15"/> and Actions, the Principles and Effects of them. The too great Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Readineſs and Frequency of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and that on the bad ſide, to Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, Accuſe and Condemn, and this moſt-what raſhly, that is, without Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Uncertainly, often Falſly. Nay, not being content with this, on all Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions without any Reaſon or Cauſe but Self-love, Pride, Hatred, Envy, Flattery, Curioſity, Buſibodineſs, or the like, to make it known and declare it to others. Whereby they diſpoſe themſelves to be Unjuſt and Unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to others, and hardly to like any Body but themſelves, or thoſe that are like themſelves, or ſome way or other Uſeful and Profitable to them, that is, themſelves in others. And as much do they diſpoſe others by this their Behaviour and Temper, both by way of Imitation and Revenge, or Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, at leaſt to behave themſelves in like manner to them, and to pay them in their own Coyn. Men hereby too, growing Strangers to themſelves, and being buſier in other Mens Tempers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47246:15"/> and Actions than their own, are taken up in mending in others that which is not Faulty, or they can leſs mend if it be: While they neglect themſelves where it may be more to be mended, and where they can better do it.</p>
               <p>A Vice or Fault, this ſeems too Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary frequent. For what more frequently comes into our thoughts and Diſcourſes at all times, than other mens Perſons, and conſequently their Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and Actions. All our Behaviour to one another, to all ſorts of Perſons, ſuppoſeth and followeth our Judgments we make one of another; which are very rarely exactly true, and ſincerely Charitable; but moſt-what altogether raſh and prejudiced by Self-love, and conſequent Paſſions, or blended and mixed. Few Men alſo employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in Judging, or Diſcourſing of things appertaining to Perſons abſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from Perſons, becauſe they are not accompanied with a ſenſible Subject; which with what appertains thereto, they beſt apprehend and conceive: And for the ſame Reaſon among others, the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47246:16"/> Perſons are others, not themſelves, they moſt frequently occurring to their Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Men ſeldomer ſee themſelves in their Glaſſes, than others directly with their Eyes: And then they being great, but as fooliſh and unreaſonable Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovers, are not only willing therefore to have nothing Faulty, Bad, or Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in themſelves, which is well: But alſo not to ſee it, and then they judg they really have none; when they have as many, or more, and greater than others; which is fooliſh and bad. Bad, becauſe it proceeds from ultimate Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love: Fooliſh, becauſe the miſtake through Self-flattery, is very Hurtful and Miſchievous to themſelves, whom they ſo much love. For hereby they deprive themſelves of the greateſt good, that is of becoming univerſally Good and Vertuous; while they overlook what is amiſs in themſelves, and ſee it not at all; or if they do, they take it for ſomething that is Vertuous and Commendable, or much more ſo than it is. Nor is this Fault or Vice, only to be ſeen in ordinary Perſons: But is alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47246:16"/> very general to all ſorts, even to thoſe who have had the Opportunity of the beſt inſtructed Education. Witneſs Books and Writings, where oft-times Men proclaim aloud, and leave upon Record; and this moſt willingly, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, fooliſhly, out of Pride, Envy, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Contempt, the Ignorance, the Folly and Miſtake, the Raſhneſs, Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, Knavery, Hypocriſie, Obſtinacy of one another. This is that which our Saviour here Warns and Adviſeth againſt in this long and Excellent Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of his, both to his Diſciples and a multitude of People, who were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together from all the Countrey about, to ſee and hear what he did and ſaid: And it ſeems they heard ſo much, as put them into great Wonder and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment. Both in reſpect it is like of the Excellent Matter of his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Diſcourſe, being more Moral and Spiritual than that of the <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi> and their <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Doctors</hi> was, who moſt-what read them Lectures of tithing <hi>Mint</hi> and <hi>Gummin,</hi> and the minute ſmall Matters of their Law:
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47246:17"/> And then in reſpect of his manner of Speaking, which was with more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: That is, ſo as to move them more to mind and believe the things he ſaid, and that (among other Ways) by ſpeaking them ſo, as if he moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly knew the Truth and Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of what he ſpake; they on the Contrary, it may be, only probably, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly, dubiouſly and coldly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning about their ſmall Queſtions.</p>
               <p>In treating of this Argument; the Summ or Contents of our Diſcourſe ſhall be theſe;</p>
               <p n="1">I. Only juſt to mention the true Senſe of the word here uſed, to Judg, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="2">II. The Judgment here forbidden, ſhall be more particularly explicated.</p>
               <p n="3">III. What Judgment here is not forbidden, though in danger of being taken for that which is.</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Whence this forbidden Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment here proceeds, what are the Cauſes.</p>
               <p n="5">V. The miſchievous Effects or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences hereof, which will be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47246:17"/> Reaſons too, why we ſhould not be guilty of it.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. The Remedies to prevent or mend it.</p>
               <p n="7">VII. How we ſhould govern our Judgments of Perſons, both concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Vertues and Vices.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>I. For the Firſt. The word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> here rendred to Judg, hath ſeveral Significa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In General to paſs Judgment, that is, to affirm or deny, any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition or Sentence thought of. This is the moſt ordinary Senſe, and every where occurs, 1 <hi>Cor. 11. 13. Judg in your ſelves,</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.] <hi>Is it comely for a Woman to Pray with her Head uncovered.</hi> And the ſame in 1 <hi>Cor. 10. 15. I ſpeak as to Wiſe-Men, Judg you what I ſay:</hi> i. e. Paſs your Judgment, give your Opinion after Conſideration, of what I am now about to propoſe unto you: And where this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is thus uſed in the Septu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agints
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47246:18"/> Tranſlation of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it may Anſwer to the <hi>Hebrew</hi> words <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and other words.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. More particularly, To paſs Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning the Actions or Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of a Perſon, either of his Vertues or Faults, Good or Bad: And this is as often met withal; and ſo it is, three or four times preſently after one another, in 1 <hi>Cor. 4. 3, 4, 5. But with me it is a very ſmall thing, that I ſhould be judged of you, or of Mans Judgment: Yea, I judg not mine own ſelf:</hi> That is, As for yours, or any Mans Judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Faithfulneſs in my Stewardſhip, of the Myſteries of the Goſpel (of which in the two former Verſes) whether I am, or am not Faithful, I make a little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it. Their Judgments upon many Accounts, it may be, being but little, if any probable ſigns of the Truth. Nay, I paſs not Judgment concerning this thing Univerſally my ſelf; I, it may be forgetting, or not ſeeing many things in my ſelf: But the Lord is he that doth always, and hath right to Judg, who is All-knowing and Juſt, as it is in <hi>Verſe</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:47246:18"/>3. More particularly yet: It ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to paſs Judgment concerning a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Innocency or Merit, that he is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent: That is, an Acquitting and Abſolving him, ſo is the Senſe: <hi>To Judg the Cauſe of the Poor and Needy.</hi> Spoken of <hi>Jehoiakim</hi>'s Father. And, <hi>To Judg the Fatherleſs and Oppreſſed, that the Man of the Earth may no more Oppreſs,</hi> Pſalm. 10. 18. Here, and in ſuch like the Septuagints word is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, anſwering to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. On the contrary, it oft-times ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies to paſs Sentence or Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Perſons Fault, or Guilt, or Puniſhment he deſerves, that he is Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and deſerves Puniſhment; that is, to Condemn or Accuſe. For in both this is done, in the one as a Judg, in the other as a Witneſs: And therefore it ſignifies the ſame with its Compound, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>Condemn.</hi> This is alſo a moſt frequent Senſe of this word, both in the New and Old Teſtament, as <hi>Rom. 14. 3, 4. Let not him that eateth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him that eateth not: And let not him that eateth not, judg him that eateth.</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:47246:19"/> That is, As he that did Eat, and was ſo well informed in his Liberty, of the good Effects of it, as to put no Diſtinction between Meats, upon the Account of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Divine Command, but only his own Prudence, was not to deſpiſe the other for his Ignorance: So he alſo who did make ſuch Diſtinctions, was not to condemn the other of Unconſcientiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Prophaneneſs; that is, Neglect or Contempt of his Duty commanded by God's Revelation. And in <hi>verſe</hi> 4. is the ſame Senſe, <hi>Who art thou that Judgeſt?</hi> that is, Condemneſt another Mans Servant. Where, by the way, you muſt take Condemnation in the Senſe I ſhall by and by limit, as alſo underſtand it here between private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and with this Circumſtance, that it was before the Chriſtian <hi>Jews</hi> had time to inform themſelves well, and to underſtand the Reaſons of this Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and to get rid of their Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to believe ſtill the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Law, to be obſerved even under the Meſſias's Government: But that by the Bye.</p>
                  <p>And to go no further, <hi>ver.</hi> 10. ſtill
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47246:19"/> of the ſame Chapter, <hi>Why doſt thou judg, or why doſt thou ſet at nought thy Brother?</hi> That is, ſurely, Why doſt thou ſo judg thy Brother, as after Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to contemn him, and to deſpiſe him? But ſuch a Judgment muſt be, that he is Faulty, or Ignorant, and that is to condemn him. Now which of theſe Senſes the word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> here hath, I ſhall by and by tell you, when I more explicately and diſtinctly inform you, what Judgment it is that is here for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>To give you yet a more diſtinct No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the General Senſe of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, it is to be obſerved, that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts of two Parts. The Firſt is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Action. The Second, the Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of it.</p>
                  <p>The Firſt, Is to paſs Judgment only in a Mans thoughts, ſilently in ones own Breaſt.</p>
                  <p>The Second, Is to ſignifie this our Inward Judgment to others, by Words
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47246:20"/> and Speech, or any other convenient Sign. I obſerve this principally, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it may be permitted and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble oft-times to do the Firſt, when it is not to do the Laſt. A Man may, nay ought often to give Judgment concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things and Perſons; when he may, and ought not for many Reaſons to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie it. Such as are the Circumſtances of the Perſons Faults, who may be a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour, a Governour, a Friend, one o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe very Wiſe and Innocent, or one either through Baſhfulneſs, or Wrathfulneſs, not able to bear it, or many the like: So the Circumſtances of Company, either that there are any, or too many, or ſuch as will make more ill uſe of ſuch a Judgment of ours, may make it reaſonable and juſt, to abſtain from making known our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And many ſtill, other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances may there be, for theſe are but to give Inſtance.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:47246:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>WE proceed to the Second General, <hi>viz.</hi> What kind of Judgment may be here Forbidden, or Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt, what this may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> more Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly. And they may be among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, theſe Six things, ſome principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and firſtly, ſome occaſionally and ſecondarily.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Too great a Proneneſs, Propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, Inclination, Readineſs to paſs any inward Judgment in General, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Mens Qualities and Actions.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Too great an Inclination to paſs this Judgment on the worſt ſide, to judg them Imperfect or Bad, to attribute ſome Defect or Infirmity to them, or to accuſe or condemn them for ſome Fault.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To paſs this Judgment without any Reaſon at all oft-times but only a Mans will: Sometimes indeed with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47246:21"/> ſome Reaſon, but little, ſlight, ſudden or in general, not with ſo much either on one ſide or t'other, as a Man might and ought to have found out and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: When one doth not ſpend ſo much Time, nor uſe ſo much Care, Heed, and Attention, in the Reaſon of his Judgment as he ought, which ſometimes is more, ſometimes leſs, according to the Import<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce of the thing judged, or rather of the Judgment. And this is called Raſhneſs, or Temerity, a raſh Judgment, a raſh Cenſure of others.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To paſs this Judgment contrary to the Reaſons even appearing to us, (which muſt always proceed out of ſome bad Principle next to be named) ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with ſome appearing Reaſons, but falſly. And this is called Falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which we ought to do what we can, when it is permitted us to judg, to prevent.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Too great a readineſs to declare, ſignifie, talk of theſe our Judgments; and that is, principally to do it upon all Occaſions not ſufficiently Reaſonable, nay, upon none at all.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:47246:21"/>6. And laſtly, Above all (in which only the Blame, Fault, Viciouſneſs, Iniquity, is to be found) a bad Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or End of our Judgment concerning others, which is but too often the cauſe of all the other Imperfections. Such as is a want of Charity, Hatred or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Self-love in General, Pride, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of Superiority, Envy, and the like, of which hereafter. In all the former we may be Defective, Wanting, Imperfect; but here we are Wicked, Bad, Unrighteous.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>1. Too great a Proneneſs and Readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to paſs Judgment, concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in any Reſpect; which is always concerning their Qualities of Power, or Knowledg and Wiſdom, or their Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or their Actions hence proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. I ſay, too great an one; for all paſſing of Judgment is not here prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, as I ſhall hereafter mention. Now this too great a Proneneſs or Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is Various according to Perſons,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47246:22"/> and muſt be determined by every Mans Prudence, when it is ſo. In ſome Men it may be much their Calling, their Buſineſs, it may be what is committed to their Care, for very excellent Uſes and Purpoſes to obſerve and give Judgment of others. And therefore they are to bend and incline themſelves to get ſo much Readineſs and Aptneſs, or Quickneſs, to obſerve and judg, as may make them beſt able to diſcharge that Truſt. Such are all kind of Governours, who have the Care of others Qualities and Manners; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, Miniſters, thoſe who have the Education of Youth, Maſters of Families. All theſe will do ill if they do not take notice, and judg concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Tempers, and Behaviours of their Subjects, People, Youth, Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants, as much as they can, without too much Neglect of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or other worſe Effects. Again, There are ſome that obſerve others to very good Uſe and Purpoſe: what is Good, they are prone to imitate; what is Bad, to ſhun and avoid: and this that
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47246:22"/> they may clearly apprehend Virtue and Vice; which oft-times we better ſee in others, than in our ſelves. What is uſually ſignified by the Proverb, <hi>That Standers-by ſee more than Gameſters.</hi> Men oft-times would neither be ſo Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their own Virtue nor Vice, Good or Ill-Qualities, if they did not obſerve them in others. When they ſee a Man practiſing any Virtue, cr uſing any good Quality of Prudence, Diligence, any Inſtance of Power right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and well, and eſpecially when com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended or thought well of, or having ſome other Advantage; it makes them well pleaſed with themſelves in theſe things, if they have them, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to obtain them, if they want them. And ſo Vices often appear to us more and more ugly and naſty in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, than in our ſelves: Such as is Intemperance, Pride, Oppreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what may the Obſerver ſay, Am I like ſuch a Perſon? I did not think I had been ſo Fooliſh, ſo Contemptible, Baſe, or Vile a thing before. Theſe Men too are ſo far from neglecting
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47246:23"/> themſelves thereby (the common Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief of our concerning our ſelves ſo much with others) that they mind them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hereby the more, and to better purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>But now on the other hand, but few Men are Governours of others at leaſt of many: many alſo obſerve and take notice of others good Qualities, and are thereby excited to affectation of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Superiour, conſequently to envy Detraction and Contempt. And you ſhall ſee them judg and ſpeak often of the moſt conſiderable Men, and the moſt conſiderable Qualities in them, with Abatement and Diminution; which as it may not ſometimes, ſo it moſt-what proceeds from the above-named Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples. They'll take notice too, more ſurely of their Imperfections, and be apt to be moved to be well-pleaſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, from the former Principles ſtill; and conſequently to multiply and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them. Now it were a great deal better for Men of ſuch a temper, to withdraw their Eyes from abroad, and to turn them home-ward, unleſs they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47246:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> could or would make better uſe of their Obſervation; and readineſs in ſuch Men to Obſerve and Judg others is too much, and therefore here forbidden. Others again there be, who may and do take notice and obſerve what others do, and are generally with Approbation, and be ready to imitate every thing, and it may be the worſt things moſt. Thoſe who you ſhall ordinarily here ſay, that ſuch Perſons do ſo or ſo, that they may excuſe themſelves; theſe it were better for them to neglect and take no notice of other Men, and not to mind what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do. It is much better for thoſe Men to mind what they themſelves ſhould do, than what others do. Here again a little proneneſs to mind or judg what others are or do, is too much.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>2. The Second thing I conceive may be here forbidden, is too great a Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to paſs Judgment on the worſt ſide, to attribute ſome Imperfections to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to accuſe and condemn them.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47246:24"/> And this may be, though our Judgment be not falſe, (which is another Particular forbidden) but never ſo true; nor do we yet conſider or attend to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from whence it proceeds, but only to the effect which is conſequent; and here again as in the former Particular, the Degree forbidden is various. Some Perſons may and ought to take notice of, Judg and Condemn other Mens im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and faults (but always be ſure, with as accurate truth as they can, with Prudence and Charity) more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and frequently, others rarely or little. Thoſe as I ſaid in the former Particular, who are Governours of others ſo far forth as they do and ought to undertake that Office, ſo much ought they to take notice, obſerve, judg, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn, yea, reprove and correct (but always with Prudence and Charity, of which more hereafter) their Infirmities or Miſdemeanours. Thoſe alſo who do it out of no worſe end, nor find no worſe effect, than the good one of freeing themſelves from too general and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed admiration of other Mens Perſons,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47246:24"/> and conſequently Approbation, imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all they do, though many things weakly and amiſs; finding themſelves firſt without Self-flattery, able to Judg from other Reaſons than Examples.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe alſo who having a deſire to be more exquiſitely and accurately perfect and good, mark the Imperfections or Miſcarriages of Men, and that of the beſt and moſt conſiderable, that they may prevent and amend them in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and be more accurate Patterns and Examples of Accompliſhment and Virtue. Not out of Pride or Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be Superiour to all others; but out of a great deſire of perfecting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and out of Charity to others.</p>
                  <p>Such Perſons of ſuch a Temper, though very rarely I doubt, we may ſometimes meet withal. So likewiſe when Perſons, Eſtates, or Qualities are of great concernment, and influence to us and others, to the Publick, and this preſently and on a ſudden; and our Judgment might tend to prevent any miſchief there-from, which defer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red would be too late in ſuch Caſes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47246:25"/> Sufficiency and Tendency to judg or believe rather on the worſt ſide, is to be preferred. The contrary would be too pernicious or hurtful Security. Such as theſe, I ſay, and Men in ſuch caſes, are to be allowed more frequently, to employ themſelves in obſerving and judging other Mens Imperfections or Faults, in their Temper or Conduct. But theſe on the other hand, who may experience not elſe-where better effects of this their Obſervation and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than an occaſion and temptation for, and a gratification of their Pride, Self-love, Envy, Affectation of Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riority, Malice, Ill-will, Revenge, or the like; ſo far forth as they experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence this ſo much to them is it Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited.</p>
                  <p>And in general, it may be delivered as one pretty general ſign, when we may do this too much (there ſeldom being a better effect than this, a bad one) <hi>viz.</hi> When thereby we are indiſpoſed and hindred to take notice of, and approve of the good qualities and laudable that are in the ſame Perſons, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:47246:25"/> judg of them in general very unjuſtly, and are according unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably affected towards them, undervalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, contemning, hating them; that is, the qualities in them when we ought not, or more than we ought: And this we may ſee, I doubt, too frequent and common an effect, of this Judging and Condemning Perſons; in ſo much that there are very few but may be hence concluded to be too much inclined and prone thereto, and to do it but too much. Where you hear one or once commended, and his good qualities ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, you may hear many, and many times diſpraiſed, and his Faults and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections quoted; at leaſt oftner than they are really in proportion to their good Qualities and Actions, or oftner than they ſhould be ſignified and made known.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>3. The third thing I conceive may be here forbidden, is ones Judging with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Reaſon at all, but only ones
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47246:26"/> Will and Inclination, or without ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Reaſon, the beſt he could or ought to have had all Circumſtances conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that is, raſhneſs or temerity in Judging, and when it is on the worſt ſide, to condemn any Perſon, it is now uſually called raſh Cenſure. Of the firſt of theſe there is no Degrees or Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, but it is perpetually in all Perſons at all times forbidden. For if there appear no Reaſon at all to us, why we ſhould judg one or t'other way, we are to ſuſpend our Judgment. That which is uſually expreſt by ſaying, we do not know, we cannot tell, it may, or it may not be ſo indeed; (if we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the poſſibility) but whether it be or be not, we are Ignorant. In our Judgments concerning ſome things, we may ſometimes follow our Inclinations both without and contrary to ſome ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Reaſons; but then they muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrong, ſuch as are natural and born with us, and which we cannot oppreſs or hinder by our wills though we would, and we do not find they proceed from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Inſincerity, any ſecret deſire or incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47246:26"/> to gratifie any Luſt, but that we are poſſeſt with a ſerious and upright unmixed deſire to know the truth in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Goodneſs: And this, indeed, ſeems to be a ſign of great reaſon for that Judgment, <hi>viz.</hi> Of this inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being Impreſſed by God, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently he being Good, that it is true and uſeful. Such are Mens ſtrong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations notwithſtanding all appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of reaſon (though but ſuch, and and real deceits) to the contrary, which may be brought by Cavilling men, to believe God's Exiſtence, his Juſtice to puniſh and reward, Immortality of Souls, diſtinction of Actions right and wrong, univerſal Goodneſs our great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and ultimate Self-love, contrary to the truth of our Senſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe God hath anticipated us withal. But in our Judgments concerning Perſons, no ſuch inclination is to be followed by no means, which notwithſtanding is extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary frequent, but always from ſome ſecret paſſion of hatred, diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure againſt the Perſon, not for any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but ſome bodily temper which is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:47246:27"/> called Antipathy, and oft-times paſt offences, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the other, <hi>viz.</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without ſufficient reaſon, there is variety; that which may be ſufficient reaſon to one Man, or at one time in one thing, may not be to another. One Man may be more capable and able to examine a thing further than another; and yet both, may be, ought to paſs their Judgment: As if one Friend ſhould for very good ends, ask the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſome other, concerning the Qualities or Actions of a third. So ſometimes the time for Deliberation or Information, may be neceſſarily ſhorter in one affair than in another; and yet the Judgment is then to be paſſed too, and not neglected: And ſo the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning one thing of leſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (and yet enough to deſerve and require our Opinion too) may be with leſs reaſon or probability, than another of greater Importance. And here this raſh Judgment is not to be allowed on either ſide, as well to the advantage as diſadvantage of the Perſon, concerning his good or his ill-qualities or actions.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47246:27"/> We are not to judg Men better than they are, as well as not worſe; and conſequently falſly and fooliſhly admire and approve of what they ſay or do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon, only becauſe we will, and as we ſay we imagine ſo; not with that ſufficient Reaſon as we ought to have: Though the extream of Judging Men raſhly better than they are, being leſs frequent or hurtful, I ſuppoſe the other is here principally intended, <hi>viz.</hi> The Judging Men raſhly worſe than they are, and cenſuring them.</p>
                  <p>This Imperfection very often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from <hi>Ultimate,</hi> and therefore <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate</hi> Self-pleaſing our ſelves by meer Activity of this kind. We muſt be paſſing Judgment of every thing we ſee, or that appears to us, and as ſoon and as faſt as may be; we cannot ſtay ſo long as to call to mind, or examine Reaſons. This is too troubleſome to moſt, and would ſpoil the pleaſure of it: Oft-times Men make it their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion but imprudently choſen, to be at any rate wantonly Judging and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſing of Perſons in general. Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47246:28"/> alſo the Cauſe or Principle is Self-pleaſing again, by the exerciſe and ſenſe of our ability and ſufficiency of Wit or Underſtanding; we much pleaſing our ſelves that we can obſerve what others do and judg, and diſcern whether they are good or bad, do well or ill, eſpecially what the moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Men do; and here moſt, becauſe it is a ſign of a greater Comparative ability, that we ſee Imperfections and Defects, even in the Wiſer and Better ſort of Men, which they do not (as we think) ſee in themſelves. The firſt of theſe Cauſes is more ordinary, the ſecond in thoſe moſt often, who really are of conſiderable ability. Theſe are more innocent Cauſes as not arguing ſo much of Self-Love, in oppoſition to the good of others or to Charity; as the other of Malice, Hatred, Revenge, Pride, Affectation of Superiority, and thence ſecret Envy which are but too frequent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:47246:28"/>
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>4. The Fourth thing forbidden is falſe Judgment, which although it may be more hurtful in effect, yet it may be and often is more innocent in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple or end, than the former. For a Man may often judg falſe and out of Charity and Duty too, and with as ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient reaſon as he could find or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. But yet a Man having firſt ſeen he may or ought to paſs his Judgment, ought to adhibit the greateſt care that it be true: This is a great inſtance of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice which as every Man at all times is bound to, ſo then eſpecially when he undertakes to be a Judg.</p>
                  <p>The moſt general Inſtances of raſh and falſe Judgment concerning Perſons, Qualities and Actions, and perhaps which comprehend all others, are theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When we Judg imperfections, defects, faults, of any kind or ſort to be in Men, when they are not.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When we Judg thoſe to be much greater imperfections, than indeed they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47246:29"/> are compared with others, we miſtake in the quality. The firſt again is, Firſt, Either when we judg Imperfections to be in Men one or more, when either there is none, or not ſo many. When we miſtake in reſpect of the Number. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, When we Judg more of that which is; a greater Degree and a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Conſtancy of theſe Imperfections, which really are in the Perſons, to be in the Perſons, than there is, we mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake in the Degree and in the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation or Duration: And thus on the contrary alſo, we often judg as raſhly and falſly of our ſelves, or any we fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, or who are Friends to us.</p>
                  <p>We judg perfections and good qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to be in our ſelves and them, and more of theſe Perfections in number, and them to be greater, and more of each of them in Degree and Frequency, or Conſtancy, than indeed there is; when all this is a miſtake, and oft a ſilly or wilful one, and on the contrary judg ours and our Friends Imperfections and and their degrees of Intention and Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency fewer, and the Imperfections
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47246:29"/> leſs than indeed they are; and we to that purpoſe conceal, connive at, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them willingly, even to our own Conſciences and our beſt Friends, and this out of <hi>ultimate</hi> and fooliſh miſtaken Self-love. A thing often to be obſerved in ſick and dying Perſons, very back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to take notice of their ſins and faults, and the degrees of them, and to reckon them up all, and to make a frank acknowledgment to their own Conſciences or their Friends. A ſign too of no very great degree of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, or a Converſion from ſin. In the firſt, we multiply and magnifie the Imperfections, Infirmities, Defects, ill-Qualities of others: Here the good ones. Surely much the better extream as to its Effects (as it ſeems) even when it proceeds from <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-love, as well as the other extream (which is too often) and not out of Charity.</p>
                  <p>A more particular and very uſeful Inſtance of the Firſt General is, when we Judg the Actions of Men to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from worſe Principles, Ends, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Qualities in them, than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47246:30"/> they do. A thing the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and carefully to be avoided, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of very miſchievous and evil conſequences, and yet extraordinary frequent and eaſie to be fallen into. Thus often we accuſe and condemn Men of Covetouſneſs, Pride, Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiouſneſs, or the like, from ſome actions which really were the effects much of a wiſe and diſcreet Virtue, and had very little mixture if any of theſe Vices.</p>
                  <p>A thing very often, eſpecially hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening in refuſal or denying, the Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and Deſires of others.</p>
                  <p>Thus we accuſe Men often of great Wilfulneſs, when it is Weakneſs, of Wickedneſs or Evil-diſpoſition of Will, when it is Ignorance and Imprudence; of deliberate Miſchievouſneſs, when it is a ſudden Surprize. How often ſhall you hear Men fiercely accuſe one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Malice, Hatred, Revenge, Pride, than the firſt of which nothing more deviliſh and worſe, can be thought or ſaid of a Man, (though I wiſh it were not ſo often true) when there is no ſuch
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47246:30"/> matter, but an impartial and upright Juſtice; that is, Charity to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, or at worſt ignorance, miſtake, Mens not attending, forgetfulneſs or the like. This is very often ſeen in the behaviour of Sects and Parties one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Where the Inconſiſtency of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions with good Conſcience, is often fiercely affirmed too univerſally, before it is known what Advantages they have had for Information. Though I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg too, there may be oft very ſufficient ſigns for a very probable Judgment: This raſh and falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe or the like Inſtances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo miſchievous, and yet frequent, is (as I ſaid, when it is on the falſe ſide) diligently to be avoided; and rather let the defect, the raſhneſs, and the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take, be on the other hand; which uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally argues much of Wiſdom and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, good Nature, and a great free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from <hi>ultimate</hi> and inordinate Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love, and eſpecially when it is towards Adverſaries: And therefore it is a love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and amiable thing, it is called good Interpretation and Candour. When
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47246:31"/> one judgeth moſt favourably, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the beſt ſenſe and meaning upon Actions and external appearances, when there is equal probability on both ſides, or there is none at all of either appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and when it is conſtrain'd to judg worſe, it is with pity: According to that invaluable <hi>13th Chap.</hi> of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> to be written in the moſt deep and laſting Characters in our Souls, and to be read every morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nay, as oft as may be, <hi>verſe 5. Charity as it beareth all things, ſo it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and hopeth all things.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>5. The Fifth thing forbidden, is, too great a Proneneſs and Aptneſs to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, to declare and make known our Judgment and Opinion concerning others, eſpecially on the bad ſide: To be always talking thereof, though to no viſible good effect, nor out of any good Principle. And to be in pain as it were till they have delivered themſelves, and this uſually comes too from the <hi>Inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:47246:31"/> love of Activity, of doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what, of Reſtleſneſs, which is called Buſibodineſs; and ſometimes from the other worſe Qualities ſo often mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Malice, Pride, Envy, Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and moſtly from a mixture of more of them together: With all which too, as in all other Actions of Men inſincere, (as moſt are I doubt) ſome ſmall mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſometimes there may be of Juſtice, that is, of a kind of common Charity. This too great Proneneſs or Inclination conſidered without its Principle or End, (as I have told you before) admits of Variety. Some Men ought to have more, as all Governours and Overſeers of others Manners, or in general of their good Qualities. Thoſe alſo that find the good effects of good Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Self-amendment, kindly and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Emulations, Pity, an endeavour for the good of the faulty, and of others, to amend or prevent the ſame elſe-where. Others on the contrary who are private Perſons, in a private Capacity or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, apt to gratifie thereby their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Pride, Hatred, Contempt of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47246:32"/> Self-conceit, affectation of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, will have ſeldomer ſufficient rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to paſs or declare their Judgment; and when they have, the good effects are not ſo conſiderable in them as in the former Perſons: Conſequently they muſt nouriſh a leſſer Proneneſs and Inclination thereto. Theſe Men alſo who find they can better diſcern, chooſe, govern, and Inſtruct themſelves in all Circumſtances, of declaring their O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion concerning Perſons, ſuch as I have before mentioned, of the Perſons judged, the Perſons before whom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe alſo may be more free, and allow themſelves more of this Proneneſs. Thoſe on the contrary, who may and ought to obſerve themſelves forgetful, unable to take notice, or diſcern the fitteſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; or not to be able to moderate or govern themſelves when they do, but what they have in their mind it muſt come out; thoſe who are thus dull and weak, ought to lay aſide this Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Inclination, to ſubjugate or weaken it ſo far forth, and to betake themſelves more to mind their own af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs immediately.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:47246:32"/>
                  <p>In General (of which more hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) the declaration of this our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, muſt always be done with all the ſigns, and with the beſt effects we can of Charity, in doing Good, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Self-denial. Charity, I ſay, ſometimes more immediately reſpecting the Perſon of whom we judg, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our ſelves, it may be, (as in the caſe of ſin, when we ought to vindicate our ſelves) ſometimes ſome others, By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanders, ſometimes altogether: Be ſure let there not appear any the leaſt ſign of doing it out of <hi>ultimate</hi> reſpect to our ſelves in any kind, nor let the effect be only ſuch with a neglect of, or in oppoſition to the good of the Perſon, or others. And a great many ſigns there are of this, which may better come in in another place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VI.</head>
                  <p>6. And laſtly. And above all is here forbidden, the undue end of our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-pleaſing <hi>ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mately,</hi> and that ſeveral ways, by others
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47246:33"/> hurt or miſchief, poſitive or privative: Theſe are, Malice, Hatred, Pride, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Revenge, Flattery and baſe Fear, Buſibodineſs, Curioſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is that which is here principally intended; this mainly advis'd againſt by our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; as alſo judging on the worſt ſide, ſuſpecting, accuſing, condemning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons out of the foreſaid Principles. As appears by the reaſon ſubjoyned both in this and the next Verſe, [<hi>Judg not</hi>] is here taken in the ſenſe in which [<hi>that you be not judged</hi>] is: But by that is meant ſuſpected, accuſed, condemned by others, principally out of the former Principles. For if it were meant of the Judgment of the good ſide, the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding of that would be no motive not to judg, becauſe it would not ſeem an evil to the Perſon judging. I ſay, principally: Moreover, I have mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the defect of being too prone in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral to paſs Judgment, though it may happen on the good ſide; and ſo to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare ones Judgment, and to judg raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or falſly, though ſtill on the good ſide on this occaſion, as belonging to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47246:33"/> our Judgments, to ſuggeſt unto you, that they might be occaſionally forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den too, and are Defects, Infirmities. All the forementioned Particulars, if they can be ſuppoſed to proceed not from theſe bad Principles, but from good, <hi>viz.</hi> Charity, though impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and miſtaken; though they may be immediately hurtful and do miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, yet they are not vicious, faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wicked. But more of this when we come to the Cauſes of theſe forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Judgings here, eſpecially of raſh and falſe ones.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>BUt what Judgments are here not forbidden, though they may be apt to be miſtaken for thoſe which are. And in general theſe two, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. Not an obſerving or judging out
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47246:34"/> of <hi>Charity,</hi> a ſincere and unmixed <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> For ſometimes, ſurely, we may exerciſe our Charity both in good and bad Judgments. The principal thing here forbidden, is paſſing our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of bad Principles, ſuch as are <hi>Ultimate</hi> Selfiſhneſs, Malice, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, Pride, Envy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But then the contrary cannot be forbidden to paſs Judgment out of a good one, and the only good one, <hi>viz.</hi> Charity, or Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, unleſs all Principles of a Mans actions were forbidden.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>Nor, Secondly, Is it ever forbidden to a Perſon, when there are more good effects of his doing this, than of his omiſſion: Nay, then contrary-wiſe he is commanded to do it. The firſt reſpects our Principles or End: The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond our Prudence or the Effect. The firſt of theſe may be without the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> A Man may give his Judgment and Opinion concerning Perſons and Actions, out of Charity and very good
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:47246:34"/> Intentions of doing the moſt good unli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitedly in general, whether it be parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly applied to our ſelves or others, or both; and yet, as far as we ſee, the effects of it may be bad. A Man may both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly and outwardly commend and diſcommend Perſons unſeaſonably with a very good meaning, through want of Information. And ſo the ſecond may be without the firſt too; that is, There may be very good effects and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of a Mans paſſing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his Judgment, when the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple may be bad enough. A Man may approve or condemn what is truly good or bad in others, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſe himſelf and others to an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the one, and an eſchewing of the other, eſpecially if he be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome eſteem; and yet he may do the firſt out of fear or flattery, or becauſe it is like ſome-what in himſelf, not becauſe it is a quality or thing real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profitable to the World, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would have it more propagated. And the ſecond out of Envy, Hatred, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> not becauſe it is a thing miſchievous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47246:35"/> and hurtful to the Perſon himſelf, to others, or diſpleaſing to God Almighty.</p>
                  <p>In ſumm, whenſoever it doth appear to any Man that it would be worſe if he did not paſs his Judgment, that there would be worſe conſequences thereof than if he did, any where to others as well as himſelf, conſidering himſelf but as any other Perſon, juſt in the ſame Circumſtances; and to do it for this very reaſon and cauſe, this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good; this, I ſay, is not here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, But more particularly there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the firſt place, it is not univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally prohibited here to paſs Judgment. In the Caſes and Circumſtances I have formerly mentioned, and innumerable more (if we deſcend to particulars) it is not. It is much permitted, nay, enjoyned to Governours, ſomewhat leſs to private Perſons. Laudable it is in Men to have regard to, and obſerve the qualities and actions generally of thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47246:35"/> that are their Superiors, to compare their own with, and ſee their defect, and to be excited to Amendment and Imitation: To look at, and to judg their own faults in others, if thereby they find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves diſpoſed to ſee them more clearly in themſelves, and to be put in mind of them. Laudable it is to obſerve good qualities in others that we may rejoyce in them, and be glad to ſee any thing good in the World, and be able to encourage it by a diſcreet Obſervation and Commendation thereof. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently we are not commanded to be negligent, and utterly careleſs of what other Men are or do: For this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the former generals of Charity and Prudence, we ſhould then be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited both thoſe. Out of Prudence and Charity to our Neighbour, both good and bad Men, and to our ſelves too, we are obliged to take notice of them what they are and do; to encourage and help, or to rejoyce in what is good, to check, hinder, and prevent what is bad and miſchievous in the World, by our pity and juſt endeavours. We are not ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47246:36"/> to ſay with <hi>Cain, Am I my Brothers keeper?</hi> Yes, we are all ſo, that is, we ſhould be ſo: We are not like Brutes, to live only within our own Skins, to care for no Body but our ſelves, and inhumanly to ſay, What care we what others do? We'll look after our ſelves; let them be good or bad we matter not, we think it beſt always to mind our ſelves; we ſee Men buſie themſelves too much about others matters. In the firſt of which thou art bad and wicked, being only ſelfiſh; in the other miſtaken and imprudent. Thou art always to have regard to the common good in all thou art and doſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when thou applieſt thy ſelf to mind thy ſelf, and to do good to thy ſelf, it muſt always be to fit thy ſelf to do moſt good in general, it muſt have that for the end. Thou art alſo often (and thy own prudence muſt determine, for it may be too often) to ſtep out and ſee what others do and are, and concern thy ſelf charitably and prudently for thy Neighbours, and to pleaſe and ſerve God conſequently; there is a time when
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47246:36"/> this is beſt. Beſides, indeed thou mindeſt thy own ſelf to beſt purpoſe and effect, when thou diſpoſeſt thy ſelf to be of this charitable and prudent Temper; which may ſometimes be beſt done by uſe and exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>Fourthly, Nor in the next place is it prohibited univerſally to paſs Judgment on the worſt ſide, to Accuſe or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn; for it is permitted to the Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeers of others Manners, and Inſtructors, and Teachers of good Manners; and to Friends, whoſe care and induſtry for the good of thoſe whom they thus judg it will excite; to thoſe that would free themſelves from too partial an admiration of Perſons; to thoſe who have a mind and deſign to be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curately good, in things of more great and publick Concernment; and in many other Circumſtances, which every ones private prudence muſt determine. Much leſs ſtill is the contrary command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or indulged, <hi>viz.</hi> To judg that good
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47246:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:47246:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:47246:38"/> and laudable which is bad and to be condemned, to judg falſly on the beſt and favourable ſide: for to judg falſly is ever forbidden, and to judg accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Truth when we do judg, is always commanded and enjoyned. We are not neither to think well of all Perſons, and all in Perſons, to praiſe, ſpeak well of all things. We may and ought, when Charity and Prudence are the reaſons of our uſing our Judgments, to think of things as they are, to think that bad or faulty which is ſo, as near as we can be informed, and to ſay ſo too; as it follows in the next particular.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>Fifthly, Nor in the next place is it here univerſally forbidden to declare and make known our Judgments, and that on the worſt ſide. But there are many Circumſtances in which it is of much better effect ſo to do. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to reprove (always with Charity and Diſcretion to be ſure) the Guilty or Faulty, and to let him know our
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:47246:38"/> Opinion concerning any Actions, or Temper, or Quality in him, may be of excellent uſe, and be a means to amend the Perſons, and to prevent the like for the future. Sometimes to admoniſh others, leſt they imitate or do the like; we may make known our Judgment to them, eſpecially when the faulty Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is Incorrigible, or to prevent ſome fraud, or hurt or miſchief that other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might be done by one to another: We are not always to hold our Tongue, nor conceal all ſigns of our Opinions, be Meal-mouth'd for fear of diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or the like cauſes; which as it may be in the effect very miſchievous, ſo it proceeds uſually from Treachery or Cowardize. Much leſs ſtill is it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or permitted here to ſignifie a contrary Judgment, to what we really have in our Breaſts; to ſpeak or otherwiſe ſo to behave our ſelves as if we thought well of, approved and liked that which we do not: To do this out of the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of preventing any evil, or procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any good from a Perſon, is called Flattery. We are not to ſay, <hi>That
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47246:39"/> evil is good, or darkneſs light.</hi> We are not either for fear or favour, to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend and Praiſe what in our Judgment and Conſcience we condemn. But when we think our ſelves obliged to declare, and make known our Opinion and Judgment concerning any Perſon or Actions, it muſt always be with Truth, although it be to diſapprove or condemn. But then to be ſure, let this be always done with a ſincere inward Charity, and all the juſt ſigns of it, and of freedom from any Self-deſign, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially that which is in ſuch a caſe moſt ordinary and ſuſpected, <hi>viz.</hi> from Pride and Imperiouſneſs, and therefore with Modeſty, with great Diſcretion and Prudence; that is, a diſcerning and fore-ſeeing when it may, and when it may not be of good uſe and effect to do or not do it: Of which hereafter under another Head.</p>
                  <p>Here is to be noted, that as theſe Actions of Judgment are not prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſo not all Inclinations thereto.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:47246:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> We proceed to the Fourth General Head. <hi>viz.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>TO Inſtance in ſome of the Cauſes of theſe prohibited Judgments here, thoſe eſpecially which are more Proper, Immediate, Frequent, and moſt in our own power to prevent.</p>
                  <p>We muſt run them over again. And <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of too much Proneneſs to judg in general the Cauſes ſome of them may be:</p>
                  <p>1. Too much Idleneſs: By which I mean not a Man's doing nothing (for that cannot be, every Body is always employ'd, his Thoughts are always taken up about ſomewhat) but a Mans not having any deſtined or ſet-purpoſed-Employment, which one ſhould always chuſe, as that in which he can beſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47246:40"/> ſerve God and the World, do moſt good in his Generation. A neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning nor purpoſing to purſue always, (or at leaſt but when any extraordinary occaſion happens) any particular, nor his General calling, as is uſually diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; neither that which he with ſome others employ themſelves about, nor that which all Men ſhould, ſuch as Reflection upon ones own Actions, the end, deſign, the event or effect of them; the having reſpect to the pleaſing of God, and doing good ſome way or other to our Neighbour, to the Publick, and the performance of ſome general Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to God and our Neighbour, which all are conſtantly obliged to perform. Men's not having, I ſay, conſtantly ſuch deſigned, purpoſed, and ſet-em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, gives their Mind leave, lets them at liberty to wander about any where, to be employed about any thing that ſhall from any cauſe be thruſt upon them, or ſhall occur. Now this is far more uſually others Perſons and Actions than themſelves; partly becauſe they are far more the object of our External
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47246:40"/> Senſes, which affect Men generally more ſtrongly and frequently than any thing from within themſelves; and then what we have propoſed or objected to us, we naturally and laudably are prone to be judging ſomewhat or other concerning them, or appertaining to them. But Men that have any ſet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Calling to employ themſelves in, and beſides perform their general Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to God, their Neighbour and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are not ſo much at leaſure to mind and attend to what others are and do, and conſequently to judg. Juſt for Example, as Idle wandring Beggars, who, as we ſay, are never out of their way, and have no certainly deſigned Place or Buſineſs, turn to every By-Houſe to ſee who dwells there. They look upon, obſerve, talk to or talk of every Paſſenger they meet; when the Man that hath ſome deſigned Affair or Buſineſs, with certain time and place in his Journey, hardly obſerves or minds, or but very little and paſſingly, the Company upon the Rode, nor any way diverts or ſtops himſelf: Such was
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:47246:41"/> the fault of the younger Widdows which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> bids <hi>Timothy</hi> to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe: <hi>They learnt to be Idle, wandring about from Houſe to Houſe;</hi> and then, <hi>They were Tatlers and Buſiebodies, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things which they ought not,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 13. This is a privative Cauſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>Secondly, The Love of Activity <hi>meerly, ultimately,</hi> to no better end but only to pleaſe themſelves therein. Themſelves are too little a Sphere, there is more variety of things to be obſerved and judged in all others who they know, than only in themſelves; whence they do it with greater life and vigour, Men think it a dull thing (and that's their only reaſon) to mind principally themſelves, and things appertaining to them, and it may be the ſame things too for the moſt part, to live in a round; not always, but ſo much as is for moſt Men moſt expedient. And then when Men do obſerve or take notice of others Perſons, qualities, and actions, they will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47246:41"/> be paſſing Judgment, becauſe there is more of Action, than in ſuſpending, doubting, or meerly obſerving. That ſeems to be a ſlow dull thing too in compare with a Mans briskly and ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and uninterruptedly paſſing Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Beſides that, ſuſpending, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, being Ignorant, argue an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and this fault may have the name of Buſibodineſs, <hi>viz.</hi> When out of love of being Buſie, meerly to be always doing ſomewhat, and that with vigour and ſmartneſs, Men employ their Thoughts in Obſerving and Judging other Mens, either Qualities or Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Not out of any Neighbourly or Charitable Principle; not becauſe they ſee a great deal of good they may do by it, and therefore would do it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly; that is, not out of Reaſon, Prudence, Charity. Men oft-times Buſſle and are Buſie in the World, and they know no other Reaſon but that they love to be ſo; and nothing more often occurs about which they may be ſo, than what other Men are or do.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:47246:42"/>
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>Thirdly, The third cauſe is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Curioſity; that is, a Mans plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf <hi>meerly and ultimately,</hi> in knowing ſomething he did not know before, and being very much conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of himſelf there, for not directing his knowledg to thoſe things which are moſt profitable, which he can make beſt uſe of, do moſt good withal, nor attending to them. Hence it comes to paſs that Men are not content to mind, and know themſelves or their own minds (if it was leſs difficult than it is;) nor yet things more nearly Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to themſelves, which is more eaſie: But they are alſo more inquiſitive into, and deſirous to know the Affairs of others, what they are and do, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them, and conſequently to paſs Judgment of them; which is a ſign to them, but oft a very falſe one, that they do know: Becauſe we uſe to do ſo, and ſhould do ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> Paſs Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment only of things we do know. If
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:47246:42"/> we ſhould not paſs Judgment, but doubt or ſuſpend, we ſhould ſeem to our ſelves to be Ignorant; which we would not do becauſe we will <hi>ultimately,</hi> and pleaſe our ſelves not to be ſo. To doubt, or to ſuſpend ones Judgment becauſe one does not know, is but very rare and in few Tempers; but it ſhould be always and is to be preferred before Knowledg, becauſe it is a better thing, a greater excellency to <hi>withhold a Mans Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> where there is no Reaſon ſeen, where one doth not know or ſee (the Connexion of what he affirms and does) the Truth it ſelf, than it is to <hi>know the Truth it ſelf.</hi> The one is but a perfection of our Underſtanding, t'other a great virtue of our Wills, and we ſhall be the wiſer the more we thus judg, and accordingly behave our ſelves: I ſay, rather to ſay and think we do not know when we indeed do not, then to know though never ſo certainly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:47246:43"/>
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>Fourthly, A fourth cauſe may be an Inſtance or Branch of Pride; that is, to pleaſe our ſelves too much <hi>meerly,</hi> either that we have, or are reputed to have, an ability and ſufficiency to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, and direct others and their affairs too, better than they themſelves can: When 'tis only ſo conceitedly by us, and we know not others Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; or were we in them we would do the like or worſe; or if we had this ability, perhaps we had better be without it; whilſt it makes us leſs able to underſtand and direct our ſelves, by uſing our minds to Wander abroad, and to attend to others, and depriving us of the opportunities of Self-refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. It is very often ſeen, that thoſe who are extraordinary forward not out of ſome ſence of Duty to give Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, Advice, or Judgment of other Mens Concerns, are very negligent and careleſs, and unapt to follow the very ſame, when it is as uſeful and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:47246:43"/>
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> For ſome of the Cauſes of too great a Proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide, whether truly or falſly, (but not therefore, or becauſe they are true or falſe) in our ſelves, they are all either Ignorance, or ſome Ill-diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Will.</p>
                  <p>1. Ignorance, <hi>viz.</hi> Of the bad ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects or conſequences of this our too great Proneneſs, which Ignorance may proceed from Ill-diſpoſitions of Will, either on ſet purpoſe, or deſigned then when we judg; and we wilfully ſhut our Eyes, and do not attend to what might better inform us; or it may be contracted before. But it may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed too ſometimes, even from Love and Charity. So we ſee ſometimes Perſons much deſirous of their Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or others Good and Well-fare, very apt always to ſuſpect the worſe of them, and to obſerve their Beginning, bad Inclinations, and to think them ſo; but not ſo much to take notice of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47246:44"/> the contrary good ones in them; and this partly that they might timely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent any evil that may happen to them thereby. And ſo may it be in publick Affairs, and of very great and univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Concernment eſpecially, and yet ſoon out of our power; nay, ſo we ſee it in our ſelves ſometimes. Some Men being too apt to look upon their Faults and Imperfections, and to magnifie them, and to take no notice of what's good in themſelves, and conſequently to judg falſly concerning themſelves on the worſt ſide: Though this is but rare in compare with the other extream, and proceeds from an imprudent and ignorant love, not attending that they ought, and may do themſelves as much good by their being pleaſed with, and encouraged by, and thankful for the good they have; as by being afraid of, removing, and preventing any evil fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len upon them, or that may fall upon them: and not conſidering ſtill that it's beſt be ſure, all things conſidered, to judg always according to Reaſon and Truth; not to trouble and perplex our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47246:44"/> ſelves with vain fears and endeavours, and for other good effects thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VI.</head>
                  <p>Sixthly, But I doubt the far more uſual Cauſes of too great Proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide, are ill-diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Will in general, Self-love and Self-pleaſing <hi>ultimately</hi> in various In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſuch as are more particularly Self-pleaſing by:</p>
                  <p>1. Hatred of, or Malice (an habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Hatred) againſt any Perſon in general: Than which there is nothing in the World more deteſtable, becauſe the moſt Miſchievous, and it is the greateſt degeneracy from, the moſt op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite and contrary to, the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent perfection in the World, which is Goodneſs, and is uſually attributed to the Devil; that is, the worſt of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. This is when a Man pleaſeth himſelf <hi>ultimately</hi> in doing miſchief to, in vexing and hurting another Man, other Perſons. It is eaſie to ſee, how this diſpoſeth a Man to the greateſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47246:45"/> to judg any thing bad in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to whom he is thus affected. For if we thus pleaſe our ſelves in doing Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, we ſhall endeavour that we may ſtill pleaſe our ſelves, ſo to do; and that we may ſo do, we'll repreſent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as bad as we can, as great evils (whether true or falſe, it matters not) as we can. This, I ſay, manifeſtly is a Cauſe in us of being miſchievouſly affected, and of doing what we can to them: And this again, is a Cauſe to ſuch Perſons of Pleaſures and Delight. He therefore that wills the End, <hi>viz.</hi> Pleaſing himſelf by the miſchief of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, will will the Means thereto; and that's one, <hi>viz.</hi> Judging them as great Evils as we can. It is like a Man's dreſſing up another Perſon in ugly or contemptible Habit, that he might pleaſe himſelf in hating or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning him; whereas the Perſon's true and natural Make or Features, was more beautiful and comely than his own. But this is ſo truly a hateful diſpoſition, that I would be willing ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to think there is no ſuch thing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:47246:45"/> amongſt Men, what-ever there may be amongſt the Infernal Spirits, or elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in the World.</p>
                  <p>2. Though in the ſecond place, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge comes ſomewhat near it; that is, to pleaſe ones ſelf in doing evil to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man, meerly becauſe he hath done evil to him; which is a very unreaſonable thing. For why ſhould there be more miſchief in the World, becauſe there hath been ſome already? Clear contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the more there hath been, the leſs there ſhould be. I know oft-times there is a mixture of Juſtice and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defence, to prevent the like for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but oft-times too there is more pretended than there is; and when there is a love to Juſtice and a juſt and reaſonable Defence, it is a Cloak to hide much of the other too, or a Pill that hath much of that Poyſon in it. We have the more need to be Skilful and Subtle in the diſcovery of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of our Hearts; that is, the ends or deſigns that move our Wills.</p>
                  <p>Now it is here likewiſe manifeſt, that to judg a Perſon as bad and as imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:47246:46"/> as we can, will augment, whetten and ſharpen our Revenge, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently if we be ſo wickedly diſpoſed, our Pleaſure and Delight too; and as before, he that wills the End wills the Means thereto, when he ſees it is ſo: In revenge too, is often mixed the affectation of Superiority.</p>
                  <p>3. Somewhat leſs a bad Cauſe, but bad enough too, is Pride, or a Self-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>ultimately</hi> in the inſtances of our power: And here more particularly,</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) Self-pleaſing in our Superiority to others in any thing, a branch of Pride, <hi>i. e.</hi> to be <hi>Ultimately and more than ought</hi> pleaſed therewith, <hi>inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately and immoderately.</hi> A very miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous Temper and Appetite. I do not ſee that any degree thereof is allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or that it doth any good more than the gratification of the proud Perſon. To affect to be Superiour in ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent and uſeful Quality, may be an occaſion ſometimes of a Man's excelling therein, and conſequently of ſome good effect: But it is not becauſe he affects Superiority, that is not the preciſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:47246:46"/> Cauſe, but becauſe that Superiority happens to be in an excellent thing. And yet more particularly.</p>
                  <p n="2">(2.) Envy a kind of this affectation of Superiority, not the paſſion ſo much; that is, a deſire of depriving others of any Good they poſſeſs which we have not; (as is to be underſtood too, in the fore-going cauſe of Hatred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge) but the cauſe or principle of our being prone to this Paſſion; that is, pleaſing our ſelves <hi>ultimately,</hi> that we have ſome good things which others have not, and being very glad they have them not, and ſorry and grieved if they have them: And this makes us to will both that it ſhould ſeem ſo to us, and that it really ſhould be ſo. That it ſhould ſeem ſo; and therefore we wilfully judg it is ſo, that others are in general much Inferiour to us in any good thing, or leſs Superiour at leaſt than indeed they are, and therefore par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly that they are guilty or defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, where we are not, that they are ſuch or ſuch. We would have others not better, or as bad, or worſe than our
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:47246:47"/> ſelves, and are much pleaſed it is ſo, and therefore we make it to ſeem ſo to our ſelves, and wilfully judg it ſo, when it may be it is not in our power really to make it ſo. For the ſame reaſon Envy alſo makes us to will it ſhould be ſo indeed, and to endeavour it as much as we can: and therefore particularly, ſo far as we eſteem, honour, love; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward good things, that they ſhould not be honoured, beloved, rewarded, or the like, and conſequently that they ſhould not ſeem to others to merit it; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently both to judg and make known our Judgment very greedily and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that they do not, to bear witneſs againſt them. It is called Detraction, when a Man from this or ſuch like Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, is judged not to have ſome good Quality that he hath really; and Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when he is judged to have ſome bad one, which he is free from. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary temper to that wiſe Admonition of the Wiſe-man, <hi>Prov. 24. 17. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce not when thine Enemy falleth, and let not thy heart be glad when he ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:47246:47"/>(3.) Contempt, this hath an effect contrary to admiration: Admiration of any Perſon in general and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly, cauſeth a Man to judg all things in or any way belonging to that Perſon excellent, and to attribute more to him than he hath. Contempt in general of a Perſon, on the contrary, cauſeth us to judg all things appertaining to the Perſon contemned, mean or ſmall, or to attribute to him many and greater Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections than indeed are in him, in ſome ſuch manner ordinarily ſignified. Tuſh, there is no great matter in ſuch a Perſon, indeed he may be ſo or ſo: But that's a ſmall thing if he be; nay, there is nothing laudable in him, what's matter what he ſaith or doth? He is weak, ſilly, wilful, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas we ought not thus confuſedly to paſs Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but more diſtinctly; if there be any thing contemptible, yet there may be other things very conſiderable. Men alſo may pleaſe themſelves meerly in contempt of another, as a Mark or Sign (to themſelves, though it may be to no Body elſe) of their own Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:47246:48"/> and being better; and that they may more contemn and conſequently pleaſe themſelves, (as it was before in hatred) make him appear to themſelves, and judg him much more contemptible than he is. Both theſe laſt particulars are contrary to the Apoſtolical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, in that excellent Chapter, <hi>Rom. 12. 10. In honour preferring one another.</hi> Be we rather inclin'd to judg others better than our ſelves, and to give unto them the ſigns thereof, rather, I ſay, than aſſume them to our ſelves, even when equal probability of both ſides, or ſome (it may be) advantage of our own: for the more excellent effect only ſometimes of checking and controuling, and ſubduing, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under Command, that unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inordinate Self-love. Theſe three are Branches of Pride.</p>
                  <p n="4">(4.) A fourth cauſe is Flattery in Judging: That is, when a Man pleaſeth himſelf <hi>ultimately,</hi> in pleaſing any one that is an Adverſary or Enemy to the Perſon concerning whom he gives Judgment, and conſequently is well
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:47246:48"/> pleaſed to hear of his Faults or Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. A Man may uſe out of Flattery ſo often to tell his Judgment to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of a Perſon, that at laſt he may unawars come to believe it himſelf; and partly that his Flattery may not at any time be diſcovered, oblige himſelf to believe it, and perſwade himſelf that that is true, which before he did but ſay was ſo, though he thought the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And here it may be obſerved, that as too great a proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide, doth proceed from theſe Cauſes mentioned: So it is a moſt ordinary thing for the paſſing, and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially declaring ones Judgment and Opinion on the advantagious ſide, <hi>i. e.</hi> That a Man hath more of ſome good thing than indeed he hath, to proceed from ſome of the ſame Cauſes too, <hi>viz.</hi> Hatred, Envy, Indignation. For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, That a Man hath more Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, Treaſure, Honour, Power, Eaſe, Pleaſure, than indeed he hath, only to expoſe him more to the Envy or Indignation of others. And in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Men judg thus in a thing which
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:47246:49"/> they account a reward to him who they think doth not, or they would not have him either to merit or receive it, moſt commonly it is an eaſie thing from Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, to diſcern from what Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſuch Judgment proceeds: But ſome may be ſo cunning as to conceal or diſſemble.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VII.</head>
                  <p>Seventhly, For the Cauſes of raſh Judgment and Cenſure, they muſt be the ſame with thoſe of the two for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer particulars. The Cauſes of raſh Judgment in general, Idleneſs, Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodineſs, Activity, Curioſity, Pride, and of raſh Cenſure or Judgment, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Reaſon, but a Mans own Will on the worſt ſide as ſuch; are among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Hatred, Revenge, Pride, Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Superiority, Envy, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, Flattery. To which we may add Anger and Wrath, which if a Man be not very careful, diſpoſeth us to as much uncharitable and unreaſonable Judging as the former, and a Man is
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:47246:49"/> ſeldom or never to truſt his Judgment of any Perſon after that fierce and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founding Paſſion, but refer it to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time, when calmneſs and freedom from Paſſion, gives him more ability to ſee the Truth, and more impartiality to judg. And now all theſe Cauſes, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks, are ſo Unreaſonable, Inhumane, and Unchriſtian, when thus nakedly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, that they cannot but ſtir up in Souls not quite degenerate, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, dead, and ſenſleſs of what's good, many of theſe very Paſſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, and ſeem the uglieſt Objects that can be beheld. Theſe are thoſe which compoſe a Devil more, and are more eſſential to him than any other ſhape.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VIII.</head>
                  <p>IV. The Cauſes ſome of them of falſe Judging as falſe, or of falſity, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Judgment concerning Perſons, whether on the good or bad ſide, may, as in all other falſe Judgments, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to two within us in General.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:47246:50"/>1. Defect in our Underſtanding which here in this caſe is but one, <hi>viz.</hi> Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, in a large ſenſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the Abſence, or want of Apprehenſion, or of the actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Knowledg of ſomething which would influence our Judgments.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In our Will, a meer inclination to any certain falſe Judgment, whether it be from Cuſtom and Uſe, or from the Love, and for the ſake of any certain Object.</p>
                  <p>In this particular caſe of falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſome of the moſt frequent Cauſes more or leſs remotely, and ſome way or other reducible to theſe two, are theſe:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IX.</head>
                  <p>(1.) In general; meer Ignorance of the truth of things, where there is no defect of Will. So a Man may judg an action in reſpect of the effect and principle of it, to be well or ill done, when it is the contrary; and it was the caſe of the Jewiſh and Gentile Chriſtians, paſſing Judgment of one
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:47246:50"/> anothers Eating, and abſtaining from certain Meats, and obſerving or not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſome certain Days and Times, and conſequently impoſing them upon one another from their own private Opinions; not as determined by their rightful Superiours or Governours, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. Some of them through Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance judged, that thoſe who took the Liberty to eat forbidden Meats, contrary to the <hi>Moſaical Law</hi> (which they thought was ſtill even under the Meſſias to be obſerv'd) did an evil Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and out of an evil Principle too poſſibly, <hi>viz.</hi> Prophaneneſs, or want of that reſpect for God's Commands which they ought: And this probably too, becauſe they found in themſelves that if they ſhould do ſo, it would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from ſuch a Principle (which will be a ſecond Cauſe preſently to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.) The other <hi>Gentile</hi> Chriſtians judged right concerning the action of abſtaining from Meats, that it was not right; and the Non-obſervation of, or Liberty from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law was a Chriſtian priviledg, or it did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:47246:51"/> to the Chriſtian Religion: But poſſibly too they might (if they did not) judg wrong, concerning the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of theſe Jewiſh Chriſtians, <hi>viz.</hi> That it was out of Superſtition or Pride, that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> might not be in all things equalized to themſelves, and that the Ancient Conſtitutions of their Religion might ſeem more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable. From hence alſo (more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly) it proceeds, that even very Honeſt and Juſt Perſons (though much oftner in the World, it proceeds from <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-love or a mixture of it) judg themſelves Comparatively more Superiour to others in good qualities, and truly more valuable than they are, <hi>viz.</hi> They know and obſerve more their own Perfections and good Qualities, their Number, their Nature, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of their worth and excellency from their effects, than they do thoſe of others. They can tell better all the Good qualities they have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, than what are in others; many of which, or but few, they may ever have had occaſion to obſerve: They
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:47246:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> may alſo, and do ſee, and take notice of all the uſes and good effects of any Perfection which is in themſelves, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving frequent occaſion to obſerve them; but hardly of any of that which is in another; when he poſſibly could quote as many more of his. And hence (a little further) it comes to paſs, that every one extols and crys up his own Art though never ſo trivial, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers it before others, really believing what he ſaith. Hence alſo it is, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome Raſhneſs and Precipitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in inferring, that Men judg others too generally and too confidently to be Ill or Good qualified Perſons; to have more of Defects or Perfection compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively each with other, than they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have; that they have (for) ſuch or ſuch ill qualities and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (which may be true) but none or much fewer good quallities to balance them, than indeed they have; and than they themſelves would have known, if they had had ſome other opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of knowing them: They have had only occaſion or means to know the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:47246:52"/> defects and Ill qualities, and not the Good, and ſo perhaps on the contrary; and yet they do not obſerve ſo much, nor reflect upon it, nor attend unto this Caution. Now Men ought to paſs Judgment firſt diſtinctly, that at ſuch or ſuch a time, in ſuch or ſuch a perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance or action, there appeared to them ſuch defect or commendable quality, and then from thence according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of probability or likelihood in the Conſequence (which if the obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be but once, is oft but very ſmall) if there be juſt occaſion, to infer and conclude concerning the Qualities of the Perſon in general, as to number, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and conſtancy; which men common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do allin a clutter together confuſedly. There have been Men known, who have not only once but often appeared very mean and defecttive, (eſpecially in ſome Circumſtances, as in Publick, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation after Action, in haſte or with expedition) and yet have at that time been much more valuable, but could not ſhew it; and generally in other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Life, they have much
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:47246:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> exceeded thoſe who have appeared much better at certain times.</p>
                  <p>It moſt often requires a pretty long Converſation, eſpecially to more ſlow Obſervers and Reaſoners, to know and paſs a general Judgment truly concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Perſon: That which is uſually ſignified by the Proverb, <hi>Of eating a Buſhel of Salt with a Man, before one chuſeth him for a Friend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the reaſon ordinarily (to give no unuſeful Inſtance) that Men are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten judged in general better or worſe than they are by their Diſcourſes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ooks. If a Perſon hath wrote a Book in which there hath appeared ſomewhat conſiderable of Piety or Vertue, or Judgment, or Wit, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Good quality, he is generally thought more ſuch in more things, and more conſtantly than he is, whereas there is ſet down his Thoughts and Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which are more rare; whence alſo greater expectations from him in his Diſcourſe, Converſation, Employment, than are reaſonable; and ſometimes upon their obſerved failure, greater
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:47246:53"/> contempt and under-valuing of him; ſometimes (as when the Judger fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows common Opinion and Teſtimony, as moſt do) an undue admiration and approbation of all he ſaith and doth. The like on the contrary; when Men for ſome too light or ſatyrical, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Speech or Book, are judged more careleſs, trivial, ill-natured, or confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in more things, and more conſtantly than indeed they are. All which ſeems much like as if Men ſhould from one handſom or crooked-finger of a Perſon, judg confidently concerning the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Deformity of his whole Body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. X.</head>
                  <p>(2.) More particularly; an Opinion or Judgment too univerſal and unlim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that all other Men are like our ſelves: Which as it is true ſometimes, ſo it is often falſe. This comes from actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Ignorance, or non-attention of this Rule's not being Univerſal; and that other ſigns of Mens Qualities and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are to be adhibited and made uſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:47246:53"/> of, and that there is great variety in Men. So oft-times we judg ſuch an Action to proceed from ſuch a Reaſon, or ſuch a Principle, or ſuch a Temper in a Man, (ſuppoſe from Self-intereſt <hi>ultimately,</hi> Pride, or Covetouſneſs,) becauſe it doth ſo in our ſelves, or at leaſt we are ſtrongly inclined thereto; never taking any other account of any other Circumſtances (ſuch as his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Temper, manner of Life, Actions in the like caſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) which might give us ſufficient reaſon to believe and judg the contrary. The ſame Action may proceed from ſeveral Principles, Ends, and Purpoſes: And very different and contrary Actions (eſpecially in divers Perſons) may proceed, and full often do from one and the ſame general Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, and due End. So Men are apt to judge other Mens inclinations like their own, and that ſome things pleaſe others as much as themſelves; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things are diſtaſtful, tedious, and burthenſome, becauſe they are ſo to themſelves. So many judg that the Gratification of many inordinate Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:47246:54"/> or Luſts in us, are extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily pleaſant to all Men, ſay they what they will, and Virtue and Religion is a dry ſapleſs thing to all Men; nothing of Pleaſure or Delight to all thoſe that profeſs it, but that it is taken up or pretended to, for ſome other particular Ends, and that they would be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if they dared, and would be glad to be rid of the burthen, or freed from the confinement thereof; and that therefore they are Hypocrites: And from the ſame cauſe are frequent falſe Judgments on the Good ſide, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Actions are often judged bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than they are, which is the better extream. In ſo much that very oft very Good-minded Men cannot believe that Men are ſo wicked as they are, that they are ſo Selfiſh, Unjuſt, Frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent and Deceitful, Perjurious, Fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, and Senſual, Impious and Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, as indeed they are, and ſo are as often cozened in their dealign with them, and oft-times give their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation and their Charity where they are not deſerved.</p>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:47246:54"/>
                  <p>This is ſo general a Cauſe of Errour in our Judgments concerning Perſons, that we extend it to God Himſelf, and it takes place very frequently in our judgments concerning God Himſelf. So Men judg Him not ſo much to love Holineſs, to hate or diſapprove of Sin and Vice, and conſequently that He will not ſo much take care to reward the one, or ſeverely to puniſh the other: No, He'll be Kind and Merciful, and let them alone, and Indulge them to take their pleaſure as they will, or at leaſt He will not be ſo hard to Torment or Puniſh them for what's paſt; and all this becauſe they are ſo diſpoſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and they for their parts are very indifferent to Virtue or Vice, and would let Men alone to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves therein; they ſee no great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why they ſhould trouble themſelves or others there-about. Like thoſe wicked Perſons, <hi>Pſal. 50. 21. Theſe things haſt thou done, and I kept ſilence: Thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf, but I will reprove thee, and ſet them in order before thine eyes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:47246:55"/>
                  <p>Thus ſome Men think God Envious as it were, and if not delighted, yet content with His Creatures miſery for His own Pleaſure <hi>ultimately.</hi> They think Him Arbitrary, and Pleaſing Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>ultimately</hi> in the exerciſe of His Power, and this becauſe they themſelves are ſo, or at leaſt inclin'd to be ſo. And one, yet further, Reaſon of this, is Men's <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-love, whereby they are inclin'd to, and do actually judg many things in themſelves good Qualities and Perfections which are not, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently attribute them to God, whom all Men naturally judg to poſſeſs all Perfection: Which is true, ſuppoſing the Perfection doth not neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer or involve ſome Imperfection: A thing which is of great uſe to be taken notice of.</p>
                  <p>The ſame hath been one reaſon of ſome Men<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s (the Heathens at leaſt) Idololatrical making Images, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal Repreſentations of God in Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſhape; <hi>viz.</hi> They have judged God in this reſpect in Form and Shape like themſelves, and this out of Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:47246:55"/> together with a natural Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to conjoyn things, which uſe to be in our Perceptions and Judgments conjoyned: Such as is a rational Soul and Spirit joyned with a Body of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſhape, for which cauſe among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Angels and Cherubims are ſo pictured. This is obſerved by <hi>Cicero,</hi> in the Perſon of <hi>Velleius</hi> the Epecurean, <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. de natura Deorum. <hi>Quod ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro ſine corpore ullo vult</hi> [Plato] <hi>Deum eſſe, ut Graeci dicunt <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, id quale eſſe poſſit intelligi non poteſt, careat enim ſenſu, careat prudentia, careat voluptate neceſſe eſt, quae omnia Deorum notione comprehendimus,</hi> i. e. Plato's Opinion, <hi>That God hath no Body, cannot be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: For then He muſt want Senſe, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Pleaſure, which we comprehend in the notion of the Gods.</hi> And again, <hi>Quod ſi Omnium animantium formam vincit Hominis figura, Deus autem ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans eſt; ea profecto figura eſt quae Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherrima ſit Omnium. Quoniamque Deos Beatiſſimos eſſe conſtat, beatus autem eſſe ſine virtute nemo poteſt, nec Virtus ſine ratione conſtare, nec ratio uſquam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:47246:56"/> niſi in hominis figurâ, hominis eſſe ſpeciè Deos confitendum eſt.</hi> To this purpoſe: <hi>That if Humane ſhape be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than that of any other Animal, and God be an Animal, then He muſt needs have the beſt and the moſt Beautiful. And becauſe God is a moſt happy Beeing, and He cannot be Happy without Virtue, nor have Virtue without Reaſon, nor can Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon be any where but in a Humane ſhape, therefore God is of that ſhape too.</hi> So <hi>Cotta,</hi> the Academick, in his reply to <hi>Velleius: Homini homine nihil Pulcrius videri, blandam enim conciliatricem eſſe naturam &amp; lenam ſui,</hi> i. e. <hi>Man, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thinks nothing more Beautiful than himſelf; ſo Nature flatters it ſelf. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi> in his <hi>Clio,</hi> relating that the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> made no Statues, nor Temples, nor Altars to their Gods, but that they counted them Fools who did ſo; gives this Reaſon in his Opinion, <hi>viz. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not think the Gods to be <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſprung from Men, and conſequently (I ſuppoſe) not of their ſhape, as the Greeks did.</hi> Whether this Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to judg God like our ſelves out of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:47246:56"/> Self-love, uſe and cuſtom of concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and judging, hath been the cauſe of making Images, and corporal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentations of God, or ſomething in God by Humane ſhape, among Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans or no: Yet, I think, there is but too much Reaſon to believe, that the judging God like Mens-ſelves, hath been but too much the effect of it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially among the Vulgar: I am ſure it hath a very great natural ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency thereto. And the effect (it is probable) would have been much more, if it had not been hindred by the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Doctrine, (which notwithſtanding ſome have kept thoſe in Ignorance of, who have in this reſpect moſt need of it) and eſpecially by the Admonitions and juſt reproaches of thoſe whom theſe Patrons of Images as faſtuouſly, as fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly, and falſly call Hereticks. A cuſtom and uſage ſo ſottiſh and childiſh, that never any who had their Religion from the True God, or who had any notion of His Spiritual and Infinite Nature either among <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any ſufficient reaſon for, (as the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:47246:57"/> inſtruction of the Vulgar, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) or did not contemn and deride it, until ſome Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in the times of the greateſt Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Corruption of Manners, within ſome few Hundreds of years, introduced it into the Chriſtian Church. But to return from this Digreſſion.</p>
                  <p>In Opinions and Perſwaſions: Some even of the better natured Perſons oft judg, that Men cannot be of ſuch a perſwaſion but out of ſome ill diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Will, and ſuch a particular one too, <hi>viz.</hi> Self-intereſt; that is, it is for ſome deſigned good to themſelves (beſides the being in the Truth) ſo to be perſwaded; and this becauſe they find themſelves inclin'd thereto, and if they were of ſuch perſwaſions it would be from ſuch Cauſes: Not conſidering want of Information, Ineptitude to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend things any other way but as they have been accuſtomed, a great uſage of themſelves ſo to conceive and judg, may be the cauſes of ſuch really <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alſe Opinions of theirs. Nor do I ſee it a thing but very generally to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, how far a true Lover of the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:47246:57"/> Truth, or an Honeſt-man in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, may err and miſtake. Though I think too on the other hand, very oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times other Cauſes of falſe perſwaſions are alledged, beſides ſome naughty diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Will, when it is not ſo, or but in ſmall meaſure, and this alone hath the greateſt Influence indeed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. XI.</head>
                  <p>(3.) Too general a belief of every Teſtimony or Report, whether in Talk or Books, which proceeds oft-times a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain from meer actual Ignorance, or Non-attention, that moſt Reports are moſt-what very fallible ſigns of what's true, and ſometimes none at all: That there are much better Proofs of things ſometimes from contrary Teſtimonies of better Perſons, ſometimes from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things. This proceeds alſo from love of Activity and Curioſity, of Knowing and Judging ſome-what new and freſh, and ſome-times from the worſer Principles ſo often named. All Teſtimonies are more or leſs ſigns of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:47246:58"/> what's true, according as the Perſons are more wiſe and knowing, or more veracious willing and careful to ſay no more than they know: Now how many Actions of Perſons reported to be done with certain Circumſtances, and from certain Principles and Reaſons, by thoſe who neither do, nor can know any thing of them: Or if they do, yet through temerity, raſhneſs, and precipitancy, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, ſuſpition, envy, flattery, or ſome other diſpoſition of Will, do ſo either invent or change, by adding or detracting or ſubſtituting, that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times none at all, moſt-what but little, rarely very much of what they ſay is true and to be believed. But yet what more ordinary than for Men to believe all without ſtick or ſcruple. The fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther too ſtill Reports go, through the more Perſons they paſs, they are ſtill the more uncertain, becauſe ſtill the more alteration; and as it rarely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens for Perſons who obſerve things by their own ſenſe or reaſon, to report them juſt as they obſerved them, through forgetfulneſs or raſhneſs: (Beſides that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:47246:58"/> they might not diſcern ſome Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.) So it is as rare and ſeldom for the ſame things to be convey'd from any one to another exactly, without ſome alteration. I believe that the more Cautious and Wiſe, cannot but have obſerved, that in almoſt all Reports and Teſtimonies concerning Perſons, their Actions, Principles, Qualities, or Tempers, either the things are quite falſe, or but ſome general part of them true. The more Cautious and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, Honeſt, and lovers of Truth we obſerve Men to be; the more we may in their Reports and Teſtimonies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Perſons, either on the Good or Bad ſide, defer to them of our Belief and Judgment of the truth of what they ſay; and theſe in any degree con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, are but too few. A good ſhort <hi>Memorandum</hi> of this particular is that excellent Precept, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Remember to unbelieve or disbelieve, <hi>i. e.</hi> Either to ſuſpend thy Belief, or to believe the thing to be falſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:47246:59"/>
                  <head>Sect. XII.</head>
                  <p>(4.) A fourth Cauſe of our falſe Judgment on either the Good or Bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, is our attention to, and taking notice of, or obſerving only either the good or bad Actions or Qualities, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections or Imperfections of Men, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with their Effects and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences; and not both. Whence it comes to paſs, that thoſe Perſons in whom we attend to nothing or little but what is Good, (which is ſtill the better extreme) we judg much better than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they are; and thus it is uſually in our Judgments of our Selves or our Friends, or thoſe we love and favour: But on the contrary, thoſe in whom we attend to, or obſerve what is bad or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect only, their bad qualities or acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the bad effects and conſequences of theſe; and not at all or but little of what is Good, we judg them much worſe than they are: Judg them to have done a great many and very bad actions, to have a great many and very bad qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:47246:59"/> but none or very few good. This as it is the moſt miſchievous, ſo it is the more frequent extream. Men being now ſo far from that Humane and Chriſtian temper of univerſal Kindneſs and Good-will, that they are but very few they care for, or to whom they are diſpoſed friendly, in compariſon of thoſe they do not. This again may ſometimes proceed from meer neceſſary Ignorance and want of Information. For ſometimes a Man may have ſeen, or otherwiſe known much Good by a Man, and none or little bad; either be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Man wanted his proper Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, or through diſſimulation of his temper and inclination, or for other reaſons: And on the contrary, a Man by himſelf or others, may know many bad things by a Perſon, and little Good; when he may have much in him which he had never the opportunity to obſerve, or the Means otherwiſe to know. But it moſt-what proceeds from ſome undue diſpoſition of Will, and when a Man is partially, not juſtly affected to Perſons, and as he
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:47246:60"/> ought; he is either pleaſed or diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Perſons, more than in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral he might obſerve them to deſerve or merit. Thus you ſhall but too often ſee (to give Inſtances of that ſide which is moſt to be avoided) that Men will take more notice of, and better remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber one bad Action in a Perſon, than twenty good ones; and conſequently <hi>this</hi> ſhall procure him more Diſreputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Diſeſteem, than <hi>they</hi> ſhall honour or good-will: So ungrateful and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur'd a thing, is but too much of the World: Whereas we ſhould ſay, ſuch or ſuch a thing indeed, at ſuch a time is amiſs, bad or evil; but then 'twas but once, or ſeldom perhaps; nay, I know it is oftner otherwiſe, and he hath ſuch or ſuch good qualities, there he is to be commended, that is or was well done. And this ſhould be done not to ſooth Men up, or to make them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and ſo well-pleaſed with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, notwithſtanding many ill Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Vices, and Imperfections, as not to endeavour to prevent, reform and amend them too; but to encourage
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:47246:60"/> them ſo to do; ſince they have ſo much Good in them already: And to make ones Counſel or Reproof more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al; ſince this ready taking notice and approbation of what's Good in them, is an Argument of an impartial Love, Charity, and Kindneſs to them in the Perſon exhorting or reproving. And here I'le only add by the way, becauſe it is a thing of frequent and great uſe in Humane life, that it is the ſame kind of Cauſe of our falſe Judgment of the Goodneſs or Evilneſs of things, <hi>viz.</hi> We only obſerve and attend to either the Conveniencies or Inconveniencies, the Good or Bad effects of things, but not to both together; which is oft from meer Ignorance, oftner from ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. We may obſerve it every where in publick Conſtitutions, in Domeſtick, Private and Perſonal affairs. Whence oft-times we hurry and haſte to mend things for the worſe, and are diſcontent, ill at eaſe, make our ſelves unhappy, repine, murmur, and unthankful to God unjuſtly, and without reaſon; and yet after ſome experience of the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:47246:61"/> contrary Inconveniences we are running back again, with many other miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous and hurtful Conſequences. Oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times too on the other hand, we will not ſtir to mend things, taking notice only of their Conveniencies, and not of their-Inconveniencies, which might without greater be redreſſed. The firſt generally is the defect of thoſe who affect Novelty: The ſecond of thoſe who affect Antiquity, <hi>i. e.</hi> Who inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinately and immoderately love them; either abſolutely for themſelves with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reference to any good uſe or effect, or more than what they can really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to any ſuch good uſe, doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. The firſt is commonly the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of Young-Men; the ſecond of Old: In the one being an immoderate appetite of Activity; in the other of Eaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. XIII.</head>
                  <p>(5.) A fifth Cauſe is want of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent love of Truth. Men moſt-what in their Judgments and Diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:47246:61"/> Perſons (nor is it much leſs in things, witneſs the generality of Books) look more at other things, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or not at all at the truth of what they judg or ſay; they take little heed whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be really true or no, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeldom examine, ſuſpend, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce doubtfully, or according only to appearing probability. It is true, they ſay, and think things to be true, very confidently and ſtrongly, but this not becauſe they ſee the truth of what they affirm, but becauſe they would have it true. Not becauſe their Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and Perception goes before their Judgment, and their natural affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to Truth makes them ſo judg, but ſome other diſpoſition of will; ſuch as I have ſo often named, Activity, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, Pride, Hatred, Envy, Anger, Contempt, Flattery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereas we ſhould be very careful to poſſeſs our Minds with ſuch a ſerious love of the Truth, that we may have a conſtant reverend regard thereto in all our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Speeches concerning others. And this we ſhould do without much
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:47246:62"/> trouble, if we uſed our ſelves thereto, and did but uſe to check our ſelves, and ask the Queſtion, and pauſe a little whether we know it to be true or no. We ſhould love not only to ſpeak truth with our Neighbour, but of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour too. We ſhould look upon Truth as a moſt Sacred thing, ever to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable and to be the main, if not the only perfection of our Judgments; without which we had better have none at all. We had better be utterly Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and never judg at all, than do it erroneouſly: For by that means our Actions and Reſolutions are determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and directed amiſs, and are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievouſly made uſe of. For were it not much better that we were ignorant, and paſſed no Judgment at all of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either of the quantity or quality of their Perfections and Imperfections, than by being miſtaken therein ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to neglect or puniſh the Innocent and Well-deſerving, and to be Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and beſtow good things upon thoſe that ill deſerve, and make ill uſe of them. In few words, Men judg falſly
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:47246:62"/> becauſe they will not judg truly, or are not pleaſed therewith, or at leaſt but little and in ſuch degree only that it is not effectual. For it is not every degree of love to the Truth, that will ſecure a Man from falſe Judgments of things, and here of Perſons: But it muſt be a greater degree of Love there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, than to the thing which at any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular time may be a temptation to the contrary. And if we would be always ſecure, we muſt have a ſtronger Affection thereto than to any other Object, which may occur in our Lives, more than to the favour or good-will of the Greateſt or Beſt, more than to Miſchievouſneſs, Superiority, either in Reputation for, or Poſſeſſion of any Good thing, more than to Power or Greatneſs, more than to Gain or Riches, finally any other good Advantage or Intereſt. We muſt look upon our up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs or truth of our Judgments or Opinions, as a far greater proper Good, a richer and more excellent Poſſeſſion than all theſe; whereby we do more Good than by all theſe without it. And
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:47246:63"/> conſequently be more ſhamed and afraid to be Erroneous, and live in Falſhood and a Lye, than any other evil or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing to us, except Vice and Sin.</p>
                  <p>We muſt in a general ſenſe, <hi>Buy the Truth, and ſell it not:</hi> That is, prefer it before all other things that are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with it, and cauſe us to part with it, <hi>alſo Wiſdom, Inſtruction, and Underſtanding,</hi> the means to obtain it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23. 23. If we do not do thus, if we be not thus tempered and diſpoſed, if we do not judg this a greater good; we ſhall have our Judgments affected, ſtrengthened, bent, and determined by our love to other things in all Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, where there is not apparent demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, but only high degrees of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability; as it is almoſt in all affairs of Humane life. Nay, even in theſe a Man may wilfully blind and confound himſelf, or divert his attention; and if not make himſelf judg falſe, yet at leaſt hinder himſelf from clearly ſeeing and judging truly, and make himſelf doubt as it were; ſaying, when a thing cannot be denied, Truly, I do not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:47246:63"/> know, or the like; and in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhuffle and contrive to bring himſelf at leaſt to ſuſpenſion and doubt and confuſion. Every Man hath ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of love to Truth naturally, ſome more, ſome leſs, more than ſometimes to more, ſometimes fewer other things; and accordingly they are more likely, more often to judg truly. But it is and muſt be a greater degree than to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things univerſally and conſtantly, that will always ſecure from all preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices of his will.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. XIV.</head>
                  <p>(6.) The ſixth Cauſe I ſhall name is our Paſſions, both thoſe of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcible and Iraſcible appetite, as they are uſually called: Or more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thoſe that have good, and thoſe that have evil for their immediate Object. Such as are the ſimple ones of Love, Hatred, Joy, and Grief, and Deſire: And others compounded of theſe, as Revenge, Anger, Hope, Fear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe all in every Caſe, cauſe us to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:47246:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> judg to the advantage, and in favour of themſelves; that is, ſo as they may be preſerved and maintained, the Inſtances of which are every-where, and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Thus for Example: Love cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us to attribute to the Object be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved things that are lovely, whereby the Paſſion is maintained or encreaſed; and hatred on the contrary, to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, or aſcribe, or adjudg to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hated thoſe things that are hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and evil, for its own preſervation or encreaſe, whereby it is kept up or augmented, and made more keen and fierce: And all this without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the truth or falſhood of what is judged. So likewiſe what we deſire, we will think it is good Poſitively or Privatively. In deſire properly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or where the good we deſire, is a poſſeſſion of ſome good thing, we moſt readily judg the good thing a great Good, and conſequently its Poſſeſſion. In Anger and Revenge, where the good thing deſired is a removal of ſome evil or grievous thing to us, by doing evil to it (which obtains in Inanimate things, but
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:47246:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> principally to Perſons) we are extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily prone and forc'd to judg this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval a greater good, and in order there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the evil to be removed a mighty evil. And therefore more particularly in Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom we are thus affected or paſſionated, we judg many kinds and degrees of evil or bad things to be in them, many or all, perhaps more than indeed there are, which are ſeldome but very confuſedly apprehended, and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified uſually by ſome name, to which our paſſions of Anger, Hatred, or the like have been joyned, (as that of ſome Sect or Party) whereby ſtill theſe our Paſſions are gratified; that is, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, maintained, nay, augmented and boyled up to the greateſt degree of Agitation and Violence. And thoſe Mens judgments thus from Paſſions, whereby they are maintained and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, though they may happen to be true; yet it appears by Experience, that they are more generally falſe. Their happening to be true, ſometimes makes Men oft-times juſtifie and think well of ſuch paſſionate Judgments;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:47246:65"/> whereas the truth was not at all ſeen by them, nor was it the Reaſon or Cauſe therefore of their Judgments.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Paſſions thus byaſs, and warp, and determine our Judgments three Ways among others.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. By bringing to mind and furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Invention only with thoſe things which maintain or increaſe them, and which are true; and keeping out the contrary, hindring thoſe from ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing which may abate or extinguiſh them, which are as true too. We all may have often obſerved how much we have preſently to ſay for a Perſon whom we love, how plentifully and readily our Invention is furniſhed; What long Orations we can make in his behalf and praiſe; How many excellent Qualities, and in what great Degree, appear to us in him, and we attribute to him. All which grant to be true. But we have nothing to ſay againſt him, nothing to his diſadvantage, nothing that is bad, imperfect, or faulty in him appears, or comes to our mind; when as much might as truly there have been ſaid too.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:47246:65"/> And ſo on the contrary (the worſe or at leaſt the more frequent extream) in a Perſon whom we hate, are revengeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wrathfully affected to, with whom we are angry: Then how many Faults in him, or Imperfections crow'd preſently into our Minds? All his paſt bad Actions and Qualities remembred, his preſent obſerved, nay, his future too foretold; and altogether flie about im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately in our Fancies; and we could give a Catalogue ſometimes of many hours long, and make large Declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt him; the Man hath been this and that, and t'other, all which we'll grant to be true too: But then, how barren are our Inventions for him, we have nothing or very little to ſay to commend him. This would be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dry Theme for us. We remember, or take notice of nothing conſiderable in him: Whereas it may be here is as much, and as true to be ſaid by any other Perſon who is Calm and Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, not thus poſſeſſed by theſe Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions againſt him; nay, and we our ſelves can do it when we are out of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:47246:66"/> that Paſſion, when the Man is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered (except it be in that one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for which we are angry with him) he is the ſame ſtill, he is no better nor worſe, when we are, and when we are not ſo affected to him; 'tis we only al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and change. And ſo in particular Actions, how eaſily can we, by how many Arguments, commend, juſtifie, or excuſe any Action of our Friends, and with as many diſcommend or aggravate that of our conceited Adverſary, whom we are in hatred with, or bear grudge againſt, or are wrathful and angry with? Hence therefore we give falſe Judgments concerning Perſons quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or actions; judging them much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or worſe than they are; we having only Arguments and Proofs on one ſide brought to our Mind, by our paſſions, and thoſe on the other kept out by them. Which is like, as if corrupted or bribed Officers ſhould permit no Witneſſes to come into, or appear in the preſence of the Judg, but thoſe that ſhall ſerve for that ſide or the Cauſe that they are bribed for: And yet often our Mind
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:47246:66"/> and Reaſon, the Judg, not attending and taking notice of this Bribery and Partiality of theſe Officers, the Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (though it might and ſhould) may think it very truly judged; at leaſt as it ought according to the Evidence that it had; and ſet down, and be content, and think all was well done, and truly they were very honeſt and ſincere in their Judgments. This is one of the moſt ſlie and cloſe Cheats and Tricks we by our Paſſions put upon our Reaſons. The more had we need here to be cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and now more eſpecially when the Deceit and Cozenage is diſcovered. And both on this and the two following, as well as other accounts, it is a ſpecial Maxim of Wiſdom, not to truſt thoſe Judgments, where Paſſions have gone before Reaſon: But do one of theſe three things. Either, 1. Be calm and and have no Paſſions at all. Or, 2. If thou wilt for Invention-ſake have any, then paſſionate thy ſelf equally on both ſides. Or, 3. Raiſe up in thy ſelf a greater and commanding paſſion for Truth, which will make all the Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:47246:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> and Proof thou haſt in thy keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, appear equally on all ſides. But here I may prevent what is to be ſaid in another Head.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. And very briefly: Our Paſſions cauſe us to judg in favour of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, bringing into our Minds what is true on one ſide, and keeping back what is ſo on the other, but alſo by thruſting into them more than is true: And therefore we obſerve in our Friends and in our Enemies, (that is, to whom we are ſo) more vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues or faults, fine or foul things, and more of them too than any Body elſe not alike prejudiced can ſee, or than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there are. And,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. When things, on both ſides do come to our Minds, as eſpecially when ſuggeſted by another, who would diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe or defend the Perſon we are paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionated for or againſt; I ſay, when this is, by thruſting them on one ſide away again, or turning a Man from them, or cauſing one wilfully not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to them; or if that cannot be, not to the Proof and Evidence that is in them;
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:47246:67"/> nay, not to be able, it confounding and agitating our Minds, and drawing their force another way: And ſo it is by every days Experience obſerved, that he that is under the paſſions of Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and Anger againſt any thing or Perſon, will not attend to what can be ſaid or propoſed in their Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Defence; nor will nor can oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times apprehend the Proof or Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence thereof. So on the other hand, Timidity, or Fear, or Scruple to judg amiſs concerning Perſons, eſpecially on the bad ſide, may cauſe many not to judg according to the beſt probability that doth appear to them, without any prejudice from any Perſon, or ill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of Will: But this is an effect of Paſſions, more viſible and more to be obſerved by the Perſon himſelf miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judging, than the former, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in that reſpect more eaſie to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented. And here we ſee manifeſtly one of the principal miſchiefs of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, as there are alſo very good uſe of them; and how much therefore it concerns us to govern them well.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:47246:68"/>
                  <head>Sect. XV.</head>
                  <p>(7.) Another Cauſe of falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment either on the good or bad part, may be all Appetites whatſoever, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe which have Truth and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Juſtice for their Objects. By which Juſtice, I mean, nothing elſe but ſuch a love of, and deſire to do Good to each particular, as is moſt conſiſtent with, or productive, or effective of the greateſt Good of the whole; that, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways with regard to, meaſured and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derated by this. I ſay, all Appetites beſides thoſe; not only thoſe which cauſe it on the bad ſide, as Malice, Pride, Envy, Revenge, (which two laſt ſeem mixed of the two former) and others which have been formerly men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd; but thoſe alſo which cauſe it on the favourable ſide, as in Flattery, when a Man by paſſing his Judgment before another concerning himſelf, or his Friend, deſires to pleaſe him, and to gain his good opinion and favour; nay, partial and imprudent Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:47246:68"/> it ſelf may be the Cauſe. As when a Man having no Self-end (more than the pleaſure of the Action) in giving his Judgment concerning a Perſon to whom he hath a ſtrong inclination to do good, but without that due actual heed to, or fore-ſight of the Hurt or Evil that may come of this his Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to him, or to others elſe-where, or at ſome other time, that is, partially or imprudently, judgeth him more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving than in truth he is.</p>
                  <p>To give particular Inſtances of falſe Judgments from theſe Cauſes would be endleſs; only one may be obſerved for Example, which is frequent and of conſequence.</p>
                  <p>Contradicting the Judgment of others, paſſing Judgments contrary to thoſe of others; and oft-times the more, by how much the Number or Reputation of thoſe others are the greater. When we ſee one praiſed or diſpraiſed by them, contrariwiſe to diſpraiſe or praiſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in general, or quoting particulars, and multiplying and magnifying of them. Generally this is out of Pride,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:47246:69"/> that we might Equalize, or be Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to others in our Invention, or Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, or Honeſty, the Abilities which fit us for Judging; that we might not at leaſt ſeem to our ſelves or others, to be inferiour in thoſe Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities; that others might not ſeem as if they were only able and fit to do it.</p>
                  <p>In all which there is affectation of Superiority, Vain-glory, and Oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Envy; which are ſeveral Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Pride. And this we ſee not only among the Vulgar, and in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Converſation, but among the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; who often when any Author is generally commended (and it may be too much) ſet themſelves to multiply and magnifie his Faults and Defects, but to diminiſh his commendable Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, by concealing or extenuating them. And on the contrary, when an Author is now out-done, and thought to be much exceeded by another, and therefore comparatively undervalued, they endeavour to multiply and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie what is Good and Deſerving in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:47246:69"/> him; but to neglect, conceal, or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen what is Bad and Defective: And conſequently by this unobſerved pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, they give falſe Judgments con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them. I know theſe Inſtances may proceed from a careful Veracity and Juſtice, becauſe Men commonly both praiſe and diſpraiſe exceſſively, and their Judgments may be true; but it is more rare even to have any thing thereof, but much more rare ſtill to ſee this without ſome mixture of the other Cauſes.</p>
                  <p>And here we may juſt take notice of one reaſon of the aptneſs of Men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminate, to accuſe their Accuſers though never ſo Juſt and Modeſt; or preſently to quote their Infirmities and Faults, <hi>viz.</hi> Men know that by poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Perſon to whom they are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed with Hatred, Envy, Anger, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt him who accuſeth them, they ſhall cauſe him to judg confuſedly, and in general the Accuſer a bad or ſilly Perſon, and conſequently all that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertains to him, and conſequently his Teſtimony; and that therefore it is not
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:47246:70"/> to be believed. We ſee this deſign moſt-what to take effect with the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, where there is almoſt always Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge too.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. XVI.</head>
                  <p>The Cauſes of the Fifth prohibited Judgment, <hi>viz.</hi> Too great a Prone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to declare and make known our Judgments, may be and uſually are the ſame now often mentioned in ſome of the former, <hi>viz.</hi> Idleneſs, <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-pleaſing by Activity, Curioſity, Vain-conceit of ones own ſufficiency and ability to judg of others, fancied Reputation therefor; alſo by Hatred, Revenge, Pride, affectation of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, Envy, Contempt, Anger, Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: And Perſons who are too prone thus to do on the worſt ſide out of ſuch Principles, eſpecially now named, one or more of them, and are frequent and buſie in doing of it, are thoſe who are called properly Tale-bearers; concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whom you have ſo many Adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Book of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:47246:70"/> of the miſchievouſneſs of their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, as <hi>Prov.</hi> 26. 20, 22. and 16. 28. and 11. 13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. XVII.</head>
                  <p>Laſtly, For the Cauſes of Mens paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Judgment in Thought and Speech, concerning Perſons on the worſt ſide, out of ſuch bad Principles as are afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named; I have no other now to name, but only the corruption of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and inclinations thereof when born into this World, by ſome certain Cauſes, and this improved and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by too conſtant an ill uſage of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their wilful compliance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; few taking care to correct and amend by the Grace of God, what is bad and amiſs in themſelves, their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Degeneracy and Corruption, their Inordinacy and Immoderacy of appetite, but ſwimming down with the Stream, and doing that which is moſt eaſie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:47246:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> We have diſpatcht the Fourth General Head, the Cauſes of prohibited Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>THe Fifth is the miſchievous Effects or Conſequences, which are ſo many Reaſons, and ſhould be ſo many Motives to beware and to abſtain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. We ſhall obſerve ſome of theſe in each particular prohibited Judgment diſtinctly.</p>
                  <p>I. Of too great a proneneſs to judg others in general, the ill effects are theſe:</p>
                  <p>1. The firſt is, That too great a Proneneſs, and Practice accordingly, to obſerve and judg others, cauſeth us to neglect our own Affairs. The more our Eyes are abroad, the leſs at home; for they cannot be in two places. We
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:47246:71"/> cannot mind two things at once ſo different and diſtant. And it is every where by Experience ſeen, that thoſe who little take notice of what others are and do, are uſually more attentive to their own Buſineſs, and what imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately belongs to themſelves. The time that is ſpent in Reflection upon others Actions and Principles, would otherwiſe moſt-what (if we are not very dull for want of Variety) have been converted to the obſervation of our own. Such ſhamefully neglect oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to purpoſe, or ſet apart their own Actions, what they will, what they will not do; and their own Principles, out of what End, and for what Reaſon, and the execution of their purpoſed Actions, that they even forget to do what they themſelves had purpoſed and deſigned, becauſe they are buſie and employed in gazing at others. <hi>Wiſdom is before him that hath underſtanding, but the eyes of a Fool are in the ends of the Earth,</hi> Prov. 17. 24. The ſenſe may be, That a Man of underſtanding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards and looks at more often his own
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:47246:72"/> wiſdome, to ſee where he acts wiſely, out of foreſight of, and in order to good Ends; but a Fool's thoughts are ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and employed about things far from him, the moſt remote and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; that is, of Perſons and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (among others) which he can lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle make uſe of in compariſon. As the Man that looks at his own next ſteps, employs himſelf generally to better Purpoſe, than he that gazes at the <hi>Horizon,</hi> or bounds of the Heavens. Now the further ill Conſequences of thus doing, is this, that we transfer our Obſervation and Judgment there, where we can make leſs good Uſe, if any; and from thence, where we could have uſed it to much better purpoſe for the moſt part.</p>
                  <p>For, 1. Thou canſt not ſo well know that, concerning which thou judgeſt in another Man, as in thy ſelf, thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be the leſs certain, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Effects of it leſs certainly good. All our Judgments concerning others, are concerning their Qualities or Actions, and of their Actions ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:47246:72"/> whether they have been at all, ſometimes out of what Principle, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to what effect or good purpoſe, whether they ſhould have been done. Now, no Man can tell ſo well what Qualities are in another Man, as what are in himſelf: No man can ſo well tell the Principles of another Mans acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, his end, intention, and deſign, as thoſe of himſelf; every Man may know his own Heart better than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mans. No Man can be ſo ſure of what is done by any Man, as the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon himſelf. And laſtly, It is but rare that any Man of theſe great Talkers or Judgers, know the Circumſtances of any Mans condition, and conſequently what can or ought to be done by ſuch a Perſon, ſo well as he himſelf; and ſurely he doth or may (unleſs it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is an idle Buſie-body, or worſe) know the circumſtances of his own Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, better than he can thoſe of another Man, and conſequently what is fitteſt to be done in his owne Caſe, better than in another Mans. Why then doth he not buſie himſelf there? <hi>viz.</hi> At Home.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:47246:73"/> (I ſpeak not univerſally, but for the moſt part:) For ſometimes in ſome Caſes a Man may know other Mens Affairs better than they themſelves, and than their own Affairs, and give their Judgment with Modeſty, and out of Friendſhip. Yet how frequent is it for Men, and the moſt Ignorant and Sottiſh, moſt peremptorily and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently to judg what others who are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wiſe ought to do, what would be fitteſt and of beſt effect for them to do, to direct or find fault; where it is apparent <hi>they</hi> know little of the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of their Condition or Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and <hi>theſe</hi> cannot reaſonably be thought to be ſuch ſtrangers to their own Buſineſs and Affairs as not to know more, and to know better what they have to do, and ought to do; yea, and are as good to do it too. But that's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>2. But then, Secondly, If thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be as certain, and if another did indeed ſuch a bad Action, or out of ſuch a bad Principle, or hath any bad Quality; it may be you can contribute
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:47246:73"/> little to the preventing the like for the future, or to his amendment or help, it may be none at all, if diſtant, though thou would'ſt, he is out of thy reach, thou canſt not let him know thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or he'll not care for it if he do; but in thy ſelf thou mayſt do much, prevent the next time, otherwiſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf, nor do, nor be ſo any more, mind thy own Faults or Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Thou art without Compariſon, more in thine own power to direct, alter, or change thy ſelf, than ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man is, and yet thou art very buſie about him, and negligent of thy ſelf. Which is like as if one ſhould be very ſollicitous concerning another Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>way, and diligently obſerve whether he went right, or in a bad way (it may be to direct him too if he went wrong, it may be only to gratifie Curioſity, or to laugh at him) when he could not, or would not come at him to direct him; and in the mean time he never minded his own, and ſo perchance falls into a Slough, or Ditch, or wanders into a wrong one: Or as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:47246:74"/> if thou ſhouldſt be careful of another Mans Health, or Legs, or Eyes, which it is little in thy power to uſe when they are never ſo perfect, and neglect thy own which thou canſt uſe at thy pleaſure, and it may be have more need of being looked after, and are worſe than thy Neighbours. Or to uſe part of our Saviours own Compariſon here, to be peering into thy Neighbours Eye, and taking notice of a Mote there, when thy own Eye hath the ſame, if not a Beam: When (as our Saviour al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Himſelf intimates here) if thou pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledſt out thy own mote or beam firſt, thou might'ſt uſe thy own ſight to help thy Neighbour; but if thou ſhould'ſt pull out that of thy Neig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>urs, it may be thou canſt not aſſure he ſhall ſo well uſe his clearneſs.</p>
                  <p>2. Another evil conſequence of too great a Proneneſs, and too frequent Judgment of others, (or it then is ſo) is moſt-what an Uſurpation of anothers right, (or of that which for another to have, would do moſt good) a taking from another what is his due, it is a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:47246:74"/> piece of Injuſtice. For generally thoſe who give Judgment concerning others, would oblige them both to judg as they judg, and do ſo too, to do accordingly. They are apt to impoſe their Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and this by all the power they have, and therefore will Inflict what evil lies in their power if they do not; which may be at leaſt Ill-opinion, diſgrace, or Ill-ſpeaking-of, even in the meaneſt Perſon. They are ſeldom content themſelves to paſs their Judgment, but they would have Perſons of whom they judg, to Judg as they do, and do as they would have them, or think ſit they ſhould; and are Angry, or Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed if they do not: And here they would take away their Liberty of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their own Affairs, in acting accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own Judgment; they would deprive them of making uſe of their own Examination and Prudence, and then of determining themſelves. But is not this every Mans Right in reſpect of private Perſons? Is it not better the Judgment and Determination of a Man's own Actions for Example ſhould
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:47246:75"/> reſt in himſelf? It is true, I may give my Judgment when deſired, or asked, or where the defect of Ignorance or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity is manifeſt out of Friendſhip; but then with deferrence to the Perſons own Judgment and Determination at laſt. And this not careleſly and as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſpleaſed, becauſe he follows not me; but with an acknowledgment of his Right, and an Acquieſcence there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. Every Man is a Prince and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Moderatour to himſelf under God, in abundance of his Actions, moſt of his External, ſuch as Dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick ones, and Perſonal eſpecially; and of his Internal, as his willing, deſigning, Intentions, Opinions, and Judgments; and it is moſt for the Publick, or Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal good, it ſhould be ſo. And Men ſhould be left to the exerciſe and uſe of their own Prudence and Liberty in many things, though they ſhould not ſo well uſe it altogether as they might: The one may be a greater good, than the other an evil. Beſides, It is moſt likely, every Perſon ſhould beſt know the Circumſtances of his own, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:47246:75"/> more private Actions, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what's fitteſt to be done, or not done: Or if any did better know ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, and were better and more virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to direct; yet, How ſhould it be known when? And who would not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to it? So that there would be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Confuſion, and every one would be every ones Lord and Maſter. And yet, I dare ſay, it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, a moſt frequent piece of Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Tyranny, and running through all ſorts of Men, and lodged even in the Beggars breſt. Men are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Men ſhould be Judges in any of their own affairs, even Private and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal; but they will be judging, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting, reproving, urging, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing as much as they can, them to be, and do as they would have them, lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and domineering over others; not ſeaſonably, modeſtly, and friendly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing only. This gratifies and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Pride in us alſo, and this is that in part which the Apoſtle reproves, in <hi>Rom. 14. 4. Who art thou that judgeſt another Man's ſervant?</hi> Why wouldſt
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:47246:76"/> thou be Governour of another Man, and needs have and force him, compel him to judg and do as thou judgeſt; or elſe would'ſt hate him, deſpiſe and blame him in words too, (I ſuppoſe) if he did not, when-as in this caſe, he is only ſubject to God?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>II. The evil Conſequences of too much Proneneſs to judg on the worſt ſide, (I ſpeak as to the effect only, though the Principle be not bad).</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it leads a Man to falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to judg Perſons worſe than they are.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That it conſequently diſpoſeth a Man to Contemn, Undervalue; nay, Hate a Perſon more than he deſerves. Whence,</p>
                  <p n="3">3. It begets Suſpicions, and belief in others, that this his Judgment comes from the worſt principles, of Self-love, Hatred, Revenge, Pride, Envy, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when it really may not be ſo. Whence</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:47246:76"/>
                  <p>4. It diſpoſeth and gives occaſion, and is but too often an effectual temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, both in thoſe whom he thus judgeth and others, to contempt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and revenge toward him, and that by obſerving and marking, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king known and publiſhing his Faults and Infirmities too, which really are ſo; which otherwiſe they neither would nor ſhould have done; nay, by adding thereto, increaſing their number and greatneſs, and judging him worſe than he is, as the former had done by his Neighbour; whence further hatred and contempt reciprocally from them to him, and more than he deſerves too; hence again, it may be Hatred and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſtirred up in him again, againſt them. So that now, behold what a crowd and heap of Miſchief there is on all hands, inſtead of mutual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Beneficence. Part of this is the Motive, our Saviour Himſelf here ſubjoyns to His Command, to abſtain from Judging, <hi>viz. With what Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ye judg, ye ſhall be judged; and with what meaſure ye mete, it ſhall be
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:47246:77"/> meaſured to you again.</hi> That is, If you judg Men otherwiſe than you ought, they'll do ſo by you again, they'll pay you in your own Coyn; Men do not uſe to be behind with one another in theſe requitals: I conceive, <hi>That ye be not judged,</hi> is meant of <hi>Men;</hi> and ſo in the next Verſe, [<hi>Ye ſhall be judged,</hi>] and not of <hi>God.</hi> For God will not judg Men otherwiſe than is Right, and as ought to be; and therefore not as Men, who judg one another otherwiſe than they ought. By the way, this Reaſon of our Saviours, was an Adage or Wiſe-ſaying among the <hi>Jews.</hi> So in the <hi>Jeruſalem Targum,</hi> or <hi>Chaldee</hi> Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> i. e. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> With the ſame meaſure a Man mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, ſhall it be meaſured to him again whether good or bad, <hi>Gen.</hi> 38. 24. And again, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>i. e.</hi> Meaſure for meaſure. So they feign <hi>Judah</hi> to have ſpoken to himſelf, when <hi>Thamar</hi> his Daughter being condemned by him to be burnt, for playing the Harlot, ſhe produced the Signet, Brace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:47246:77"/> and Staff, which he had given her, and bid him diſcern whoſe thoſe were, as a puniſhment for him, who had frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently asked his Father <hi>Jacob</hi> the ſame queſtion concerning <hi>Joſephs</hi> Coat, whom he with his Brethren had thrown into the Pit, and made his Father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he was torn with wild Beaſts. This by the bye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>III. The ill-Conſequences of raſh Judgment, eſpecially of Cenſure, are:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That it diſpoſeth, uſeth, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituateth a Man thereto, both in his Judgment concerning Perſons, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where elſe.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It renders a Mans Teſtimony very inconſiderable. For who will much heed what that Man judgeth, who is known to judg any-how, without any regard to Reaſon for what he judgeth, and conſequently any ſign of truth. It is time ill ſpent to give ſuch inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, and raſh, ſlight precipitate Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons but the hearing only.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:47246:78"/>3. It gives occaſion to Men, of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Wrath, Hatred, Contempt; they always ſuſpecting ſuch unreaſonable Judgments to come from worſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples than meer Vanity and Wilfulneſs, <hi>viz.</hi> from Malice or Envy againſt them; at leaſt concluding, and truly, that there wanted the Care and Love to their Neighbours they ſhould have had: For Men ſo well affected one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, will rarely judg without Reaſon, to each others diſadvantage. Beſides, what ever the Principle be, the very ill effect will make Men ordinarily angry enough.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>IV. The ill Conſequences of falſe Judgment, are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. A Man's own Diſcredit and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reputation, for careleſsneſs, preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, inability and weakneſs, to judg right and true; whence alſo a Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validates his Teſtimony and Witneſs, and even then when he may judg well and true. He that more often judgeth
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:47246:78"/> falſe than true, gives reaſon to any Man never to believe him meerly upon the account of his Teſtimony; and therefore not even then when he may judg true. For it is more probable (conſidering meerly the Perſons Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony) that he that hath more often judged falſly than truly before, doth judg amiſs now.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The diſtribution of the Good or Evil that are in ones power, reward, or puniſhment, (thoſe of private Men I mean) ſuch as are Praiſe or Diſpraiſe, charity of Alms, or Chaſtiſement, good or bad Word, taking or commending to any Employment or Office gainful or creditable, or refuſing or diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending. I ſay, the diſtribution of theſe to ill purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> Good things to the Bad, or leſs deſerving and neglectful, or Bad to the Good and Well-deſerving.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>V. The ill Conſequences or miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Effects of too much proneneſs, or raſhneſs, in declaring ones Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:47246:79"/> unſeaſonably, or doing it when it ought not, Are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. It renders a Man contemptible, or ſome-what diſtaſtful; Either becauſe he hath not Diſcretion to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween times, and to diſcern when it is ſeaſonable and of good effect, and when not, and it is better to refrain, to hold ones tongue: Or, becauſe he cannot govern himſelf, he cannot contain his inclinations, whether from meer Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kativeneſs and Buſie-bodineſs, or from ſome other worſe Principle, he is Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent: Or, laſtly, Becauſe he will not, but out of hatred, Revenge, Wrath, or Envy, or Flattery, or the like, he chuſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to do it, and readily takes all ſuch occaſions of miſchieving another, by poſſeſſing others with an ill or mean Opinion, and by ſtirring up the ſame paſſions and affections in them againſt the Perſon, which were in himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Drawing others from their own Affairs or Buſineſs, whether it be the Perſons concerned in the Judgment, or others. Such Tatlers are like idle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who will not work themſelves, not
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:47246:79"/> mind their own Buſineſs, nor let others mind theirs: But with their ſtories con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning others wantonly divert them, or concerning themſelves fright them or accuſe them, and force them to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect their work to anſwer them, defend themſelves, or get them away.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Therefore mutual ſuſpicion, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſt, hatred, animoſities, ſlightings, envyings, contempts, or fooliſh eſteem, vain truſt, (if the Judgment be on the Advantageous ſide) too great and too general one of another: Nothing more ordinary than for Men upon the Whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or Report of ſome ill quality, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, imperfection or infirmity of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to conceive preſently too bad an opinion in general of him, and too be too wrathfully, contemptuouſly, or envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly in general affected towards him. And it were far better generally, that Men were ignorant of one anothers faults and defects, than upon the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their diſcovery, to be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable and unjuſt, as they uſually are. Beſides, theſe haſty Tatlers give no time for a Perſons Amendment uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:47246:80"/> if he hath been faulty once. But this effect is more certain, when that which is reported concerning any one, particularly reſpects him to whom it is told: As when it is ſaid, I believe he is ſo or ſo ill affected towards you, or hath done this or that againſt you, to your prejudice. For Men here are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently more Paſſionate, and ſooner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flam'd, as being in their own caſe, they are more ſenſible and fond of their own good; and this too much and beyond Reaſon, what ought to be, otherwiſe the Effect would not be bad.</p>
                  <p>There are few who have ſo much Charity and Humility, as to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg their fault or infirmity, when tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and out of good intent, or at leaſt with no bad one, it hath been obſerved, ſpoken of, and mention'd by another; or heartily to forgive, when it hath falſly, fooliſhly, or maliciouſly been done. It is better therefore generally (and theſe things are but ſo to be taken) to give Perſons no ſuch occaſions of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, hatred, contempt and envy, by eſpecially the declaration of a Mans
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:47246:80"/> Judgment, or of what he knows of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to their diſadvantage, but to be very ſparing in ſo doing; and in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral never to do it out of any worſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, than a general Charity to Men, and conſequently love to what is juſt and right; out of no ſelfiſhneſs, no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred or contempt of the Perſon in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but of love rather to him; out of hatred or contempt of the particular Vice, or Imperfection only; and one would be glad it were otherwiſe. And then as to our Prudence never to do it, but when ſeeing the neceſſity thereof, we are in Wiſdom as well as Charity, obliged to it. <hi>Be not a Witneſs againſt thy Neighbour without cauſe,</hi> i. e. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome foreſeen ſo good an effect, as ought to be a cauſe thereof, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 28. And, <hi>ver. 17. Rejoyce not when thine Enemy falleth: Nor let thy Heart be glad when he ſtumbleth.</hi> And hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to is referr'd the telling ſtories to one Perſon, of what another Perſon hath ſaid of him, or done towards him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind his back, and again to the latter, what the former hath ſaid of him. If
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:47246:81"/> this be frequent, it is uſually out of Talkativeneſs, Buſibodineſs, Hatred, or Flattery, either to do a Perſon an ill turn, by ill diſpoſing his Neighbour towards him, ſetting him againſt him; or to do ones ſelf a good turn, by get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the favour of the Perſon to whom we report, as ſeeming ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd for his Credit and good Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or other Good. Though this may be done too ſometimes out of a hearty ſincere Charity and Prudence, without any <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Where no Wood is</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) <hi>there the Fire goeth out: So where there is no Tale-bearer, the ſtrife ceaſeth,</hi> Prov. 26. 20. As Wood is uſually conceived the cauſe of Fire, ſo ſuch Stories or Reports, whether true or falſe of one to another, are the cauſe of Strife and Contention. And, <hi>ver. 22. The words of a Tale-bearer are as Wounds, and go down into the innermoſt parts of the Belly.</hi> That is, Uſually the ſtories of ſuch Perſons affect deeply their Minds to whom they are told, with keen, ſmart, violent, and piercing
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:47246:81"/> Paſſions of Vexation, Anger, Revenge. And, <hi>Prov. 16. 28. A froward Man ſendeth forth ſtrife, and a Whiſperer ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parateth chief Friends.</hi> Such a Perſon by his frequent ſtories, if he be belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, puts Enmity not only between Strangers, but <hi>Friends;</hi> not Friends only, but <hi>chief Friends;</hi> for ſo proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> may there ſignifie, it otherwiſe ſignifying Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency and Superiority. A great many ſayings you have in the <hi>Proverbs</hi> of the like nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VI.</head>
                  <p>VI. The ill Conſequences of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of Hatred, Revenge, Pride, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Anger, Contempt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The increaſe of theſe Paſſions, and their Principles in our ſelves by uſe, and in others by our example, which in the degree, or ſo far forth as they habitually poſſeſs our Souls, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us unworthy of Life or Beeing. For ſo far forth we do as much Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief as in us lies; and ſurely as far as
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:47246:82"/> we ſee, 'twere better than in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that we were out of the World. And although Self-love and Fear, may oft-times reſtrain and hinder us from being the Authors of ſuch Miſchief to our Neighbour, whereby we may be Obnoxious to humane Laws; yet there may be as much of theſe in our Hearts, as may render us deteſtable to God, whoſe Knowledg and Puniſhment we can neither conceal our ſelves from, nor eſcape. But there are infinite Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs which we are capable of doing one to another, which humane Laws cannot take notice of: In ſo much that a Place, Company, or Society, may be weary of us, and yet cannot tell how to be rid of us. Theſe diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make us like <hi>Dragons</hi> and <hi>Baſilisks,</hi> that where ever we come, we kill, and and do miſchief with our very Breaths and Eyes. Theſe are the Frenzie, the Plague of our Souls, which make every Body very reaſonably ſhun and run away from us. Finally, ſome make themſelves hereby Enemies both to God and Men, and fit company only
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:47246:82"/> for the Infernal Spirits, whom we are moſt like; and by their being as bad as our ſelves, their company will be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſutable puniſhment for us. Further, one of the worſt miſchiefs of ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and Tempers is, that by our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample we infect others, and make others like our ſelves; we make to our ſelves company of the like nature to us, and to one another: We propagate it, we give occaſion to, and ſtir up the ſame Luſts and wicked Inclinations in others; we help to make them more common and ordinary, and therefore the leſs ſhameful, and the leſs ſuſpected and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, to be ſo bad as they are.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. It expoſeth us to the Hatred, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Revenge, and Contempt of others. If theſe Qualities in us when but ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted (as in our Judgment ſometimes of the worſt ſide) were the occaſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, how much more when they but too evidently appear to be the principles of our Judgments? All prejudices of Judgment concerning others from <hi>ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate</hi> Self-love, render us generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned or hated more or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> leſs, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:47246:83"/> to the degree thereof that appears; at leaſt pitied by the Beſt and Wiſeſt. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing generally more hated than Hatred it ſelf, Ill-nature, Malignity, Pride, of which unreaſonable and unjuſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt is one ſort. I ſay, it expoſeth to their hatred and contempt ſometimes juſtly, when they judg truly of us, moſt-what unjuſtly and more than we deſerve. Men ſeldom obſerve due mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in theſe Paſſions, ſometimes by way of Juſtice, moſt what by way of Imitation, or mixture of both: And now when we are thus affected to Men our ſelves, and they by our Example, and out of Juſtice, or Ill-nature, or both, are ſo affected to us again, and to one another: How innumerable are the Miſchiefs which are conſequent? <hi>viz.</hi> Juſt all that we ſee in the World, Men are properly the Cauſes and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of one to another. All Mens miſchievous Wills and Intentions one towards another, proceed from want of Charity, from Hatred in themſelves, or from the ſame ill Qualities in others really, or ſuppoſed and preſumed;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:47246:83"/> either becauſe Men hate one another when it is not deſervedly, or when it is.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But a more particular miſchief of our judging others out of Hatred, is, their judging by way of Revenge untruly of us in general, of our Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, Principles, or Actions: Whence our Example in any thing that is Good in us, is rendred ineffectual, all our Actions though never ſo good, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not taken notice of, neglected, or interpreted in the worſe ſenſe; that is, thoſe that come from never ſo good Principles, and are very natural ſigns thereof, will be deemed Signs of bad, or meer Signs and Hypocritical. It is true, this will often happen thróugh Perſons ill-nature, and aptneſs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to judg on the worſt ſide, when there is no occaſion or cauſe on our part given, and then we being not able to help it at all, or not without loſs of time better ſpent, may do well to glance a little Pity, and ſo neglect and take no further notice: But when we our ſelves are the Cauſe, or give the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:47246:84"/> occaſion by our uncharitable, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudent Judgments of others, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpend time better than by removing them, to take away the prejudice againſt the example of any thing that is Good in our ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VII.</head>
                  <p>And thus we have run through ſome of the moſt conſiderable miſchievous Effects and Conſequences, of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Judgments by our Saviour; the avoiding of all which ought to be ſo many Motives to the practiſing of this Negative Duty: Nor ought the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary good Effects of abſtaining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from to do leſs, <hi>viz.</hi> The minding our own Affairs, the employing our ſelves about our own Buſineſs, the keeping at Home, and applying our ſelves to our own proper Works and Callings, the more accurate care of our own Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Prudence, Hearts and Actions which we can beſt know and direct, mind and make uſe of; and not only minding our own Affairs, but permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:47246:84"/> others to mind theirs, and to be Maſters of their own Principles and Actions, to examine, judg, and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine themſelves, we only interpoſing our friendly Advice and neighbourly Counſel, when asked or deſired; or when we ſee our Neighbour fails in his Prudence or Power in a matter of more conſiderable moment to him, than our time is to our ſelves or others; then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed not to be too intent to our own Buſineſs, and through Surlineſs or Careleſsneſs of our Neighbours con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, to refuſe, or not to mind, but to knock off a little from our own Buſineſs, and lend a helping-hand; like as all Men are ſo good natur'd, as to leave their Shops, and Trades, or Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a while, to quench a Fire in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Man's Houſe, though there ſhould be no danger to themſelves, or to give a Lift to their Neighbours Horſe or Aſs.</p>
                  <p>But otherwiſe not to be buſie in med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling, or tyrannical in impoſing on other Men in their own Affairs, and uſurping their Right. Moreover the
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:47246:85"/> ſecuring of our ſelves from a diſadvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous falſe Judgment, and an unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable contempt undervaluing, nay, it may be hatred of Perſons, to which that diſpoſeth us: However, from a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected guilty of the worſt of Principles of our Judgments, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently from giving occaſion and temptation to others of diſlike, Hatred, Contempt, Anger, or Revenge againſt us, and that by an unreaſonable ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in their judging of us, obſerving and proclaiming of our Faults and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; nay, and more and greater than we were ever ſo unhappy as to be guilty of, or overtaken with; which otherwiſe they would have taken no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, conceal'd neighbourly, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed. And then ſecuring our ſelves from reciprocal Anger and Wrath in our ſelves, againſt their ſo unjuſt and ill principled Judgments, to which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding we our ſelves gave a need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs occaſion, whence all manner of Miſchief and mutual Injuries; Thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing therefore of the Innocencie and Peace, mutual Good-will and Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of each other.</p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:47246:85"/>
                  <p>Again; the prevention of fooliſh, blind, unreaſonable, precipitate and raſh Judgments. The preſervation of the credit of our Teſtimony, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves thereby in a capacity of, ſometimes to the eaſe and conveniency of our Neighbours, determining or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting to determine the Controverſies or Differences between them. The preſervation at leaſt of the Credit and Opinion of our unprejudiced Charity, and care of our Neighbours Credit and Reputation; of the want of which we give but too juſt Suſpicion, by our raſh and inconſiderate Judgments, when on the worſt ſide. Further ſtill, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Diſcredit and Diſreputation to our ſelves, for our Careleſneſs, Inabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or Weakneſs to judg, or for our wilful prejudices by our falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; when we were able to judg bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, truly; nay, when it is a thing always one of the moſt in our Power of any thing in the World. For who cannot judg, and ſay, that he knows not, if he be Ignorant, and hath no probability more on one, than to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:47246:86"/> ſide, or that it appears and ſeems to him, indeed, more probable? In which he needs never to be miſtaken, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the thing may prove contrary to what appeared to him?</p>
                  <p>Further, The ſecuring us from the Breach of the material part, at leaſt of the Ninth Commandment, <hi>viz. Of bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing falſe Witneſs againſt our Neighbour.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, principally the Juſt and Beneficial diſpoſing of our Kindneſſes and Favours, and the with-holding them according to the degrees of each ones Merit or Demerit, the prudent and profitable diſpenſing our Praiſe or Diſpraiſe, Good or Bad word, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation or Refuſal, Charity or Chaſtiſement: Not to ſquander a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way fooliſhly, nay, to ill purpoſe, what Good is in our power to beſtow, and to with-hold it as unſeaſonably, when it would be to good Effect laid out.</p>
                  <p>Further ſtill; the prevention of our own being ſlighted or contemned, for want of Diſcretion, or Self-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the uſe of our Tongue and Converſation, for unprofitable or hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:47246:86"/> Talkativeneſs and Buſie-bodineſs, and of being grudged at for worſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (ſuſpected or real) of our unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and laviſh Declaration of our Judgments. But more conſiderable much is the prevention of mutual Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities, Grudges, Ill-will, Diſcords, Contentions, Strifes between Men, uſually ariſing from the ſuſpicion, or certain knowledg of one anothers ill words, actions, affections, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to, and concerning each other. Which if they had been concealed, and not too haſtily been told or diſcovered, might have been repented of, and the Perſons of another mind, and ſo no need of giving warning thereof to the Perſons concern'd, and Charity and Peace had been ſtill preſerv'd and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd. The Humility and Forgiveneſs of the World, is too little to bear the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of Mens few faults and miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages one to another, and therefore they had not need be multiplied. The prevention therefore of all the miſchiefs of Tale-bearing. Yet further, the not drawing of others from their better
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:47246:87"/> Employments, by diſturbing them with falſe, untrue, or at leaſt uſeleſs and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial judgments and Reports concerning them; which although they are eaſily neglected, paſſed over, and ſlighted by thoſe that are wiſer and better, and well provided in the World; yet they very ſenſibly touch, and much affect thoſe who are not ſo; of whoſe Good we ought, as good Neighbours and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, to be juſtly tender. Finally, and above all, the prevention of the Increaſe and Improvement in our ſelves (by uſing our ſelves to the wicked Principles of Judging, ſo often named) of thoſe helliſh, wicked, and baſe Diſpoſitions in us, to name them now and no more, thoſe of Hatred, Malice, Revenge, Pride, Envy, Contempt, Anger and Wrath, Flattery; which if we have any degree of wiſe Self-love, we ſhall more endeavour to ſecure our ſelves from, than from the moſt loathſome, tormenting, and killing Diſeaſes of our Bodies. The prevention conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of expoſing our ſelves to the Hatred and Contempt of others, but
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:47246:87"/> too juſtly deſerved, and of the loſs of all the benefits of mutual Good-will, Friendſhip, and kind and loving Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. And laſtly, The rendring our Example effectual; that if there be any thing Good in us, it might not be at all loſt and do no Good; nay, our good Example be turned into a bad one by Mens unjuſt, (but by us occaſioned and provoked) bad Interpretations of what we are, and do.</p>
                  <p>All theſe things and many more, which might be obſerved, of the like nature, thoſe Miſchiefs of doing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to our Duty, and the advantages and good Effects of the Practice of it in this particular of our Judgments concerning others, ought reaſonably to make us careful of our Principles and Prudence therein, more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, <hi>viz.</hi> That we be not too Prone to judg others; much leſs to Judg them on the worſt ſide; to obſerve, accuſe, and condemn them, even in our Hearts; not to judg raſhly, and without all Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but our Wills; not to be Inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate; not to judg falſly, but always
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:47246:88"/> when we judg, to do it exactly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Truth as near as we can; not to babble out our Judgments at any rate, not to be too prone to do that, but to do it out of Charity always, and with Diſcretion and Prudence; never laſtly to paſs our Judgments out of the worſt of Diſpoſitions, Self-pleaſing by Activity, Curioſity, Hatred, Pride, Revenge, Envy, affectation of Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority, Contempt, Anger, Flattery, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>WE are now come to the Remedies or Means to prevent thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited Judgings, of which one of the moſt General, And</p>
                  <p>1. Shall be to remember and attend to the great number of miſchievous Effects and Conſequences thereof, and then to the Cauſes of them. The
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:47246:88"/> firſt will diſpoſe our Wills to be averſe there-from, The ſecond will direct us to ſome means to effect our Wills. The firſt will make us willing to abſtain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from. The ſecond able. Call to mind therefore, and think of, as oft as thou may'ſt be in danger, how much of that time ſpent in obſerving and judging of others, might have been ſpent in Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>examination, reflection and attention to thy own Buſineſs and Affairs. How idly and unprofitably, to ſay no worſe, I employ my ſelf there, in compariſon to what I might do, if my thoughts were more at Home. How much more uprightly and prudently might I carry, and demean my ſelf in all my Actions. Again, how troubleſome and importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate it makes one Man to another, to be too frequently Checking, Control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Determining them in their own Affairs, to be Tyrannical and Injuring. How unreaſonable and miſchievous it is to be diſpoſed to Hate, Under-value, or Contemn Perſons, more than in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Judgments they deſerve, and to be conſequently the Cauſes of our
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:47246:89"/> ſelves being Under-valued, Hated, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned there-for, and more than we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. Again, the being occaſions and cauſes of Sin and Trouble, both to our ſelves and others in the World. How fooliſh is it to expoſe our ſelves to juſt cenſure for Folly, Raſhneſs, Inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Weakneſs, Indiſcretion and Partiality, and to be neglected juſtly, and not to be fit to do any good to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by our Teſtimony? The bearing falſe Witneſs againſt our Neighbour, how ſhould it pinch and wring us, and hurt us, as much as if we nip'd or cut our own Fingers, or gaſhed our own Fleſh? What a pitiable thing is it, and miſchievous, to ſee a Man miſtakenly to ſtroke the Bad, and ſtrike the Good, becauſe he thinks well of the one, and ill of the other; juſt clean contrary to what ſhould be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and like Mad-men out of their Wits? Why ſhould any Man call upon himſelf Contempt, Hatred, Anger, or Revenge, for his weak, imprudent, peeviſh, or ill-natured Tatling his Opinion of others? How hateful a thing is it, to be the Cauſe of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:47246:89"/> Hatred, Animoſities, Grudgings, Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wills, Diſcords, Contentions, Wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Brawlings, and miſchievous Actions between Men, to ſet the World on Fire, to be a Fire-brand? Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, can any Man who wiſely loves himſelf and the World, for the good of which he is made, endure, to be the Author of miſchief only, to be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of the World than in, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to ſee himſelf a conſtant Judg to condemn, and Executioner too by his Hatred, Malice, Ill-nature, Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Envy and Spite, Revenge, Anger, Pride, affectation of Superiorioty in Judging, to be a Peſt and Bane to the World, and to improve theſe moſt Noxious qualities in himſelf, by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and Uſe, and in others by the imitation of his example, and to baniſh kind and friendly Converſation? Is it not alſo brutiſh enough, and a ſign a Man hath no Mind to get any Good quality, wherein he may be an uſeful Example to others? Or if he hath, he cares not whether any be the better for it or no?</p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:47246:90"/>
                  <p>Conſider, and attend to theſe and ſuch like things, eſpecially at thoſe times when you may have moſt need, when you find your ſelves moſt prone to offend in this kind, or when upon Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on your ſelves at any time you find you have ſo done. And as we ſhall do well thus to learn and inform our ſelves in, and remember and call to mind theſe, or ſome of theſe ill Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, both when we are about to do amiſs in this kind, and when we have done ſo, to prevent the like for the future, by getting our Minds againſt it; ſo that we may know how to do it, it will be uſeful to take notice of, and remember the Cauſes that we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them.</p>
                  <p>Shun we therefore and avoid Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; let us chuſe and mind ſome Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of our own in particular, nor let us neglect our general Calling of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God, Self-examination and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, occaſional doing Good and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence. Have we a care of Buſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bodineſs, and meerly to be doing and talking, for doing and talking ſake,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:47246:90"/> but always for ſome further good end. And ſo likewiſe have we a care of Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, or a humour and deſire to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and know every thing, though moſt Remote from us, and Impertinent to any good uſe or deſign we put it to, meerly for the obſervation and knowledg ſake; and it is no matter where the things be never ſo ſmall and trivial, and in others (as they will be for moſt part) too, ſo it will gratifie that Humour in us, and that is all we care for. Secure we our ſelves from this Childiſh temper, and if we deſire to obſerve and know things, let them be Profitable and of Concernment, and thoſe which we may make beſt uſe of, and that is, be ſure, what is in our ſelves. Let us have a care alſo of that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar branch of Pride, <hi>viz.</hi> Affectation to know and direct others in their own Affairs and Actions.</p>
                  <p>But moſt Induſtriouſly let us eſchew and flee the gratification of our ſelves, by the hatred of others and revenge. Far be this from us, and Pride and fooliſh af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of Superiority, and therefore
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:47246:91"/> envy, fury wrath and anger againſt Perſons in general, as alſo Contempt, the moſt common Cauſes of Detraction and Slander. Let them not come near us, nor enter in the leaſt within any the doors of our Breaſts. Flattery too and <hi>ultimate</hi> baſe fear of any ones diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, or ſeeking of their favour, we muſt alſo deſpiſe and ſcorn, which doth ſo much betray us oft-times to Judgments on the worſt ſide of ſome, that we might pleaſe others; let us be ſure to inform our ſelves as well as we can, when we judg concerning others, and not do it ignorantly. And more particularly, let us have a care we do not too generally conclude all Perſons like our ſelves, nor ſuffer our ſelves to be abuſed by publick Report or Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and judg all true what we ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; make always an allowance one way or another; at leaſt moſt generally ſuſpect and doubt till further Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if it be worth the while. Let us have a care of that kind of Partiality, whereby we obſerve and take notice but of one ſort of Qualities or Actions
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:47246:91"/> in Men, none but their Good, or none but their Bad, as they are our Friends, or Foes, as we are well or ill affected towards them; but let us be free and indifferent to ſee both Faults and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections in our Friends, and Virtue, and what's good and laudable in our Enemies. Let us ſtir up and maintain always in our Minds a ſtrong habitual love of the Truth, which will be by and by a more particular Inſtruction. Hardly any thing of more good effect in this buſineſs, than the government of our Paſſions, to remove, calm, quiet them, if you intend to paſs any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Judgment as to Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> Love, Hatred, Admiration, Contempt, Revenge, Anger, and the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e; ſuffer we not our Minds and Memories to be Brib'd by theſe, to admit only what can be ſaid on one ſide, and not of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other; nay, more than can or onght to be ſaid, and to thruſt upon us what is not true, and thruſt out again what is or may be true, becauſe againſt them; ſuffer we not our Minds to be ruffled and confuſed by them, and not to be
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:47246:92"/> able, and willing not to attend to the evidence of what we would not have to be True, or would have to be Falſe, though never ſo manifeſt: For what can be expected from us of Truth and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in our judgments concerning o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, when we are ſo affected? And laſtly, Let us ſeriouſly endeavour to Reform, Correct, Amend the Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and bad Inclinations of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that <hi>ultimate</hi> Selfiſhneſs, ſeeking our own ſelves without any regard to the good of others, nay, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs contempt thereof, and by their miſchief or hurt; as if their good were not Good, as well as mine; hence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently Hatred, Malice, Revenge, Pride, affectation of Superiority, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, Contempt, cauſleſs Anger, Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery: Seek we, I ſay, to cure our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by Obſervation, Caution, Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, and God's Aſſiſtance. Thus if we take but heed to, and remember theſe and all other which are the Cauſes of our too buſie, diſadvantageous, raſh, ſelfiſh, falſe, malicious, proud, envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, wrathful, contemptuous, flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:47246:92"/> Judgments of others, and remove them, we ſhall certainly prevent the Effect.</p>
                  <p>But more particularly, I ſhall recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend to you ſome Remedies, which follow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>2. And therefore ſecondly, But more particularly poſſeſs we our Hearts and Minds throughly, with an univerſal Charity and Benignity to all, with a proneneſs and readineſs to do Good any where, but only where we ſee (and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſome Circumſtances, as where the thing concerns many, and is not ſo ſoon known, to conſider and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate) it will be neceſſarily the cauſe of a greater Evil; which will in general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily ſecure us. Nor let us ſuffer our ſelves to be beaten from this temper of Mind by any ill carriage, miſdemeanor, folly or injury of others. Let us ſtill retain a true love of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence for the Perſon, whatever our Keenneſs be againſt the Vice or Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:47246:93"/> Say ſtill with thy ſelf, what pity it is Perſons ſhould be ſo much their own and others Enemies, as to be guilty of any voluntary Wickedneſs; but if it be an Imperfection out of their power, then more need ſtill to be pitied and relieved by us, if we be not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in things of greater concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This will diſpoſe us to dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, abate, or connive at, and look off the Infirmities or Imperfections of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and therefore either judg favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, or not at all; except, where (as I have oft ſaid) our mutual, Chriſtian, common and univerſal Charity and Prudence, obligeth and ſtirreth us up, provoketh us to do otherwiſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>3. Rivet ſoundly into thy Mind the love of Truth; let nothing whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cauſe thee to be out of the Truth, ſcorn to feign, judg raſhly or falſly concerning the worſt diſpoſed and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Man towards thee, <hi>i. e.</hi> Contemn this Quality, but not out of a haughty
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:47246:93"/> Pride. <hi>i. e. Ultimately,</hi> becauſe it is thine own Imperfection: But out of an univerſal common Charity, <hi>i. e.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of all the Miſchief, it is the cauſe of both to thy ſelf and others. And, indeed, there is ſome reaſon why here thou ſhouldſt leſs do this; becauſe if he be faulty and imperfect indeed, there is but too much true already, why ſhouldſt thou make an addition?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>4. And yet more particularly, ask thy ſelf again and again, (eſpecially in Judgments of more Concern and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance) whether or no thou be ſure that thy Judgment be true: Stay not till another ask thee how thou knoweſt. For then for thy Credit and Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leſt thou ſhouldſt ſeem to have ſaid any thing raſhly or untrue, or out of bad Principles, thou'lt be tempted to invent ſomewhat falſly, and to feign and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg ſomewhat, it may be, true, but inſufficient, and yet perſwade thy ſelf, or at leaſt ſeems to him that asks thee,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:47246:94"/> that it is good proof. But do this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, or tacitly thy ſelf, when thy Credit may not prejudice thee againſt the Truth, but engage thee to it. And if it happen thou ſhouldſt have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot thy ſelf, be moſt ready to Retract it, and acknowledg ſo much. Ask thy ſelf I ſay, how thou proveſt it. And when thou doeſt, ſuppoſe, thy ſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the moſt impartial perſon, who hath no particular reſpect to any perſon or perſons, that is inconſiſtent with Truth and Juſtice, one that loves thee and the perſon thou judgeſt, and every body elſe; (and ſome ſuch it may be thou mayeſt have known in the World, be ſure God is ſo) whether thou thinkeſt he would admit of the proof and evidence for what thou affirmeſt or ſayeſt as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient. Then again, ſuppoſe thy ſelf in the ſame caſe with the Perſon thou judgeſt, and he in thine to judg thee: Whether wouldſt thou be content he ſhould judg ſo of thee, as thou doſt of him now? Whether doſt thou think that if he had thy Proof only for what he ſaid concerning thee, thou wouldſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:47246:94"/> think it ſufficient, and aquieſce, and grant that he had good Reaſon for what he ſaid? If thou ſhouldſt be afraid to remit the cenſure of thy Judgment to an impartial Perſon, who neither ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped nor feared any thing from thee, and was above that, but thou ſhouldſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect he would not judg as thou doſt, if it were but for a ſmall Wager, if thou wonldſt not be content thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould judg of thee in the ſame manner, and for the like reaſons (and be ſure either thou doſt not raſhly ſay, and fiercely thou wouldſt, when if it come to be done thou wouldſt not) if thou ſhouldſt find this I ſay; this ſure would put a check to thy Judgment, and make thee ſomewhat aſhamed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: But if thou didſt it in the greateſt ſincerity, then thou mighteſt and wouldeſt proceed to judg with more confidence and freedom, becauſe thou findeſt thy ſelf free from any ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples; and yet more particularly that thou mayſt try thy own ſincerity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:47246:95"/>
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>5. Ask thy ſelf whether thou would'ſt not have true, what thou judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concerning others, whether thou would'ſt as willingly it ſhould be falſe; nay, ſuppoſe it be on the worſt ſide, thou art rather inclin'd it ſhould not be true, or that thou art (conſidering that abſolutely without any further reſpect) ſorry it is true, and wouldſt alter the caſe if it were in thy power. Theſe things will principally ſerve to ſecure us from raſh and falſe Judgments, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe of the worſt ſide.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VI.</head>
                  <p>6. Uſe thy ſelf much to dwell at Home, that is, to make thy ſelf, or ſomething more immediately apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to thee, the Object of thy Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation; and particularly then when thou doſt judg another, or art about to do it, caſt a quick eye back upon thy ſelf, whether thou, it may be, art not
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:47246:95"/> guilty of that which thou condemneſt in another, or would'ſt not be if thou wert in their Circumſtances, it may be more; for aſſuredly it is a very ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing. As for example, It is moſt frequent to judg and condemn others for Pride and Covetouſneſs, out of Pride and Covetouſneſs; or reflect whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou art not guilty of as bad. Thus doing will oft-times find us more and better work at Home in our ſelves, and ſo conſequently will keep us from uſing our Obſervation and Judgment abroad, which then is too much, when it might be better employed nearer hand in our own ſelves. This will alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain us from judging falſly and raſhly, and pronouncing our Judgment with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out neceſſary ends of Charity. For we are generally inclin'd to be aſham'd, when we attend to it, to do that in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's caſe, which we would not have done in our own. Now when we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our own Faults or Imperfections, we find we are not very willing (at leaſt not gladly be ſure) to look upon them, we are loth to acknowledg them,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:47246:96"/> or judg our ſelves guilty of them, we ſhift, we apologize, excuſe, or if we can, deny; be ſure we'll have Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Truth evident (for the moſt part of us, I except ſome diſcontented Perſons with themſelves) before we conclude againſt our ſelves: Why then ſhould we not ſo do by others, as we do by our ſelves? I know no Reaſon but it is as juſt in one, as in the other caſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VII.</head>
                  <p>7. Have a ſpecial care of all Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Judgments, eſpecially of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the moſt boyſterous and rude one. Let theſe not precede, but always fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Reaſon, that ſo they do not bribe, or prejudice, or deceive even Reaſon it ſelf, as I have heretofore more particularly told you how they may, and then that they do not confound it. Paſſions, they either prejudice or blind our Judgments. The experience of this is ſo frequent, that there is none but may have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the numerous miſcarriages of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from hence. And in order to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:47246:96"/> this means, let us keep our Minds ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and calm towards others, have a care of uſing them to be affected with Paſſions immediately before Reaſon upon every occaſion. Some you may obſerve, whoſe Minds are like Tinder, or Gun-powder, which take fire always at every ſpark. And in order hereto again, uſe we Temperance and Sobriety, with moderate exerciſe, not too violent, fierce, and active, that our bodily temper may be leſs ſubject to them, leſs confus'd, dull, and yet fierce. Too much Drink eſpecially, and violent and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent bodily Exerciſe and Action diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe much to Confuſion, and Paſſions, and raſh Actions, and conſequently to blind raſh Judgments. We moſt-what ſee ſuch Perſons more Talkative, Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Opinionative, and Peremptory, and rudely and careleſly, or Proudly and Huffingly ſay any thing of others, though never ſo innocent and their Bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and very uncivilly ſullying their Names with their foul Breath. This will ſecure you from raſh and falſe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="164" facs="tcp:47246:97"/>
                  <head>Sect. VIII.</head>
                  <p>8. More particularly, be ſparing moſt to give thy Judgment concerning a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thou findeſt thy ſelf inclin'd to hate or be angry with: Suſpect thy ſelf, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain, for thou wilt be prejudic'd even undiſcernedly to thy ſelf. Or if Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances ſhould neceſſarily require thy Judgment, remember how thou art affected, ſet thy ſelf to ſhake off that prejudice; ſay all thou canſt for the Perſon firſt in thy thoughts, and be paſſionated againſt thoſe Paſſions and the Prejudice of them, that thou ſhould'ſt thereby be ſo cozen'd and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd thy ſelf, and ſo unjuſt to others. This will give check always to the bad Principles of our Judgments ſo often named, and prevent alſo many raſh and falſe Judgments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IX.</head>
                  <p>9. Diſcourſe more of Things than Perſons. Thus we have ſuggeſted to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:47246:97"/> you ſome remedies to prevent or amend the Miſcarriages in our judging con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning others. I deſire you would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and make uſe of them, and try their Efficacies, and conſequently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the many great and frequent Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs, of which they are the Cauſes, and contribute conſiderably to the Peace and Innocency of the World.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. I.</head>
                  <p>WE are now in the laſt place to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to you ſome few Rules to be made uſe of in our Judging others, <hi>viz.</hi> generally, and for the moſt part. For it is rare that any rule of Prudence, or the uſing any certain Means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our due End of Univerſal Charity, is Univerſal and never to be receded from.</p>
                  <p>1. Which cannot be too often named,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:47246:98"/> and the moſt general is: Paſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare all thy Judgments out of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that is, becauſe thou ſeeſt it better ſo to do, and more good effects of it, than not to do it; not to thy ſelf only, but any where. Out of Charity, I ſay, in general to do more Good than thou ſeeſt Harm, let it light where it will, where ever thou ſeeſt it. Which part of Good effects may ſometimes be more particularly received to thy ſelf, as to expel thy too much Indifferency and Coldneſs to the Good or Hurt of others, to the love of Truth and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to uſe and exerciſe the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and direction of thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of which as a Superiour in ſome ſort thou mayeſt have more need, as of a neceſſary quality for thy place and duty, to imitate what's Good, ſhun what thou obſerveſt Bad in others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Part of theſe good effects to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon himſelf judged, to encourage him in any good Quality or Action, to check or reſtrain him from what's bad, to adviſe him of his Errour or Fault, which but by a diſcreet and ſeaſonable
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:47246:98"/> Judgment of him from ſome other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he would not have taken notice of. Men would want conſiderable ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to the knowledg and minding of their Faults and Duties, Perfections and Imperfections, if they were, and did what they liſted, and no body ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or dared to obſerve, and paſs their Judgments concerning them. It is better they ſhould know that others, and that wiſer than themſelves are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers and Spectators. And laſtly, Part of them to others, to encourage them to follow or imitate if they be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, or to reſtrain them from Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or being drawn away, if we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve and diſcommend. We may ſee it for the good of others oft frankly and chearfully to ſpeak well of, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend in their hearing, and to reprove or diſallow according to the greatneſs of the Fault or Imperfection. And we may in ſome caſes think our ſelves reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly too cold and indifferent or dull in obſerving and ſaying nothing of what's Good or Bad in others. I ſay, let all our Judgments be with the fore-ſight
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:47246:99"/> of, and being affected with all thoſe or the like Good effects, which we may ſee may follow. And then be ſure we may conclude, that ſuch Judging out of ſuch a Principle will pleaſe God too. And then you have all the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of your one general due End of all your Actions, <hi>viz. The greateſt Good of the whole Univerſe.</hi> Here therefore I exclude <hi>ultimate</hi> Self-love, that it be not to gratifie our ſelves on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any of theſe ways before mention'd, by Activity, Curioſity, Hatred, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Anger, Pride, Affectation of Superiority, Envy, Contempt, Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I exclude alſo all Ill-will or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the Perſon, but only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Vice and Imperfection of him; nay, I affirm we ought always to have a love of benevolence to the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. The Charity I ſpeak of, muſt be an Univerſal and Unlimited one to the whole, and therefore muſt comprehend and take in every particular we ſee, and conſequently the Perſon himſelf guilty of any Fault or Imperfection. Now,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:47246:99"/> becauſe Men are oft apt to deceive themſelves and others by their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent pretences, ſome Signs when we do judg out of Charity, are theſe:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. More readineſs and willingneſs to judg every where on the Good ſide than on the Bad. This is a ſign we would have no Evil in the World if we could, not without an abſolute neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for a greater Good, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of a moſt unlimited and univerſal Charity.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. An excuſing others, and ſaying all we can juſtly and truly for them, and that ſuch an Action, which oft pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from ſome bad Principle, it might in ſuch a Perſon proceed from Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, he might be miſtaken, he might think ſo or ſo, or he might do it by Surprize, or the forces of Temptation, the Temptation might be ſtrong, and conſequently not argue a very ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Goodneſs; and if it be in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Prudence, that the Perſon might conſider well, and otherwiſe than we do, or it may prove otherwiſe than we judg. In all which, as we are to ſhew
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:47246:100"/> our Charity thus by excuſing or leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſening what we ought; ſo we are too to ſhew it by a modeſt diſapprobation of what's Imperfect or Faulty in them ſometimes, and not through Idleneſs, Lazineſs, Coldneſs, or Flattery, and fear to Diſpleaſe for the preſent, betray the faulty Perſon, or others, into too good an Opinion of themſelves, and to be content willingly to be no better. This thus excuſing is a ſign, I ſay, that a Man would willingly have as little, and as few Faults in the World any where, as might be, and conſequently of a very univerſal Charity.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A third ſign is a frequent Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our ſelves, eſpecially on the worſt ſide; that is, obſerving and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning our ſelves for our own Faults, and acknowledging our own Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. The obſervation, judging and acknowledging our own Faults and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, doth not uſe (I ſpeak for the moſt part, theſe not being univerſal Signs) to proceed from any hatred of our ſelves, is very conſiſtent with mens love to themſelves; for we do not ſee
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:47246:100"/> men hate themſelves ſo forwardly; they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove themſelves, and all they do moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what proceeds therefrom. Wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t is more likely that ſuch perſons Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments concerning others, might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from a love of the perſons judged too, and of others in general; they deal by them, as they deal by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and no worſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But when we ſee men forward to obſerve and judg others, and never to mind themſelves, it is a ſign this proceeds from buſibodineſs, or curioſity, or ſome worſe Principle: For if it proceeded from any charity to the perſon, why ſhould they not be as kind to themſelves? Cannot they ſee it will do them as much good to judg themſelves, as it will do others to judg them? And ſo likewiſe, Is it likely Men ſhould ſee any more good come on't to the World to judg others, than to judg themſelves? Is it not rather ſuſpected, nay, manifeſt to Men, that there would be much better Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, if Men more betook themſelves to obſerve and judg themſelves than others, at leaſt equal? If therefore it
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:47246:101"/> proceeds out of Charity to the World to obſerve and judg others, why ſhould not the ſame move us to do ſo by our ſelves?</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A fourth ſign is, when our Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is paſſed with Calmneſs and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty. Theſe are, firſt, Signs of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of all bad and unallowable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, and therefore of the preſence of a Good one (for ſome there muſt be.) Calmneſs is a ſign of, or rather is the abſence of Paſſions, and more particularly of Anger, Revenge, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, of our Activity, Curioſity, and Buſie-bodineſs, and conſequently of Raſhneſs, and other Prejudices. By Modeſty, I mean, a not <hi>Inordinately,</hi> and <hi>Immoderately</hi> affecting, nor aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to ones ſelf any inſtances of his Perfection or Excellency, and among others, Superiority, great Merits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther truly or falſly. This therefore where and when it is, is a ſign that the Perſon's judgment comes not from Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſneſs, Pride, Affectation of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, Envy, one kind of that (for the more we depreſs others, the more
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:47246:101"/> we make our ſelves ſuperiour to them) Contempt; nay, nor from flattery. For Fear, affectation of Friendſhip or Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, is a thing that the modeſt Man is free from too. Now by how much theſe are ſigns of the abſence of our bad Principles, the ſeveral inſtances of Selfiſhneſs, ſo much are they the ſigns of the preſence of a good one (for ſome there is always) <hi>viz.</hi> of Charity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. II.</head>
                  <p>2. A ſecond general Rule, which hath been before mentioned in other places, is always to judg truly. Here I would have it ſet down as a ſhort Rule to be eaſily remembred, and always ready at hand: But becauſe I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken ſo much of this, I ſhall now add no more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. III.</head>
                  <p>3. Have a care of all Paſſions, but eſpecially of Anger before Judgment. This hath been alſo mention'd before
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:47246:102"/> in the Means. Always judg before, and if the Caſe require it, that is, if there is no way of removing the Evil but by a deſire of inflicting another leſs, then let thy Anger follow a clear and calm Judgment: Some Reaſons in brief are, becauſe thou art in great danger of being prejudic'd, and that indiſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, to judg raſhly or falſly; and then thou doſt no good to the perſon judged, if he hear, or hear of thy Judgment. For he'l be prejudic'd againſt thy Jugdment, as being raſh, or coming from pride, or ill-will againſt him; wherefore he'l think he ought not, or on purpoſe, and out of diſpleaſure againſt thee, he will not believe what thou thinkeſt and ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt concerning him; He will have no regard thereto. Nor will others be the better, for thou giveſt a bad example. Nor doſt thou inform them; for they will not truſt thy Judgment, nor take thy Word and Teſtimony then; they'l think thou art partial, not an upright Judg. I ſay, this will be, when they ſee thee judg with fierce paſſions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, and before any reaſon aſſigned.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:47246:102"/> Otherwiſe, I confeſs, when a thing firſt calmly appears true, and of concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be judged and believed, and no other way will do but that way; then to appear warm, and not too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IV.</head>
                  <p>4. Declare not thy Judgment, when thou thy ſelf art guilty. One reaſon is, becauſe that, as hath been before ſaid, the Perſon concern'd and others, will think it proceeds not from any Charity, but from Selfiſhneſs, Ill-will, Pride, and ſo conſequently they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently flie out againſt thee, and are diſpleaſed at thee for that, and take no notice of thy Judgment, whether true or falſe. There paſſions are more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with, and they more attend to the principle of thy Judgment, than the truth of it. The reaſon of which is again, that Men being <hi>ultimate</hi> Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovers, and Proud, would have reaſon to love themſelves as much as may be; whence they are more apt far preſently
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:47246:103"/> to take more notice of others Faults than their own; and conſequently when any one paſſeth Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them more preſently to look at the fault, than the truth of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. This is the reaſon we ſee every one flie preſently in the face of the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Judger, and ask him whether he be not as bad, and leaſt of all bears his Judgment or Cenſure; <hi>viz.</hi> They think it here more than ordinarily manifeſt, that it proceeds not out of Love to them (for why then think they, ſhould he not love himſelf as well); but out of Envy, Pride, or the like. Every Man will ſay to ſuch a Man, <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf.</hi> That he is an unskilful or unfaithful Phyſician, that hath ſome by-end, who goes about, or undertakes to cure that in another Man, which he cannot or will not in himſelf.</p>
                  <q>Clodius accuſat Maechos, Catilina Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thegum.</q>
                  <p>Let us ſee thee Mend thy ſelf firſt, ſay they, and then we'll believe indeed,
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:47246:103"/> thou ſeeſt reaſon to judg another for it, and mayſt do it out of Charity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. V.</head>
                  <p>5. Or if thou doſt judg when guilty, reſolve to be Innocent for the future, and condemn thy ſelf in the firſt place, becauſe more ready to take notice of thy own faults than of others. This will give Men more aſſurance of thy Circumſpection, and Wiſdom, and Charity, and conſequently make them more attend to thy Judgment, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it according to its Truth. When thou ſeeſt (for Example) any Perſon commit any thing which offends thee, and for which thou art ready to blame or reproach him, and heareſt others do ſo: Before thou paſſeſt thy Judgment, reflect upon thy ſelf ſincerely; ſay to thy ſelf, Am not I guilty of the ſame in ſome degree or other, and cannot or will not ſee that in my ſelf, which now I am about ſeverely to reprehend in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, and it may be deſervedly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Offender, only it would
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:47246:104"/> come better out of my mouth, if I my ſelf were firſt Innocent or Penitent? Don't I ſee at leaſt a Beam in my Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's eye, when I have as great an one or the ſame in my own? There are Five Reaſons among others, why a Man ſhould firſt or equally take notice of his own faults, accuſe and condemn himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Every Man ought to love himſelf ſure as well as his Neighbour, as he would do another Perſon of the ſame qualities; and if it be good his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours faults ſhould be obſerved and judged, that he might be adviſed and amended, ſure it is good his own ſhould too.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. A Man gives a very good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to others, that they ſhould do ſo by themſelves too; which is a thing ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rare, and yet of ſuch extraordinary uſe and benefit.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. He renders his own Judgment concerning others, when he doth paſs it, more effectual, by giving to underſtand it proceeds not from Imperiouſneſs, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineering, Envy, Peeviſhneſs, or Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiebodineſs, but from a wiſe Charity,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:47246:104"/> out of a prudent Love, he doth by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers as by himſelf, he ſpares not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Every one knoweth moſt certainly the truth of his Judgment concerning himſelf.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Here Mens care and zeal will be more ſucceſsfully employed certainly; for every Man hath it more in his own power to mend and reform what he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves and condemns in himſelf, than what he condemns in others.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VI.</head>
                  <p>6. For the moſt part it is moſt ſafe, that is, of more certain good effect not to declare thy judgment than to do it. And therefore when at any time, or in any particular caſe thou ſeeſt no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of good conſequence or effects on either ſide to paſs Judgment or hold thy Tongue, rather chuſe to refrain; do it not till thou ſeeſt ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able advantage. And one reaſon is, becauſe a Man may (for the moſt part I ſay) paſs his Judgment at another
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:47246:105"/> time, may have opportunities enough to do it; but he cannot recal it when paſſed, he cannot undo what he hath done, <hi>Neſcit vox miſſa reverti.</hi> And yet the practice of Men is generally clean contrary; that is, if there be not ſomething to affright or deter them, they ſeldome refrain to ſpend their cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures very freely.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VII.</head>
                  <p>7. Be more cautious and ſparing in ſometimes paſſing ſometimes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy Judgment in theſe following Caſes.</p>
                  <p n="1">(1.) Concerning thy Superiours, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially on the worſt ſide; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, 1. As to their Principles they being far from our Obſervation, and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing few or very uncertain ſigns thereof (for the moſt part) our Judgments here will be very uncertain. And</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As to their actual prudence and fore-ſight in matters concerning their Office, it is for the ſame reaſon to us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but yet far more likely (to
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:47246:105"/> compare it with that of their Inferiours or other private Perſons) to be more and better than what is in them. For they make it more their Buſineſs to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to what is moſt for the general good of thoſe who are under their care, when Inferiours look only or principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at themſelves. And then they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally have better information what is ſo. And truly, it ſeems likely that if there were as much aſſurance of the Integrity of Governors, or their ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere love to the publick Good, as there is of their knowledg, the Judgments of wiſe and honeſt Men would general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with reaſon be for their honour and advantage; though with raſh and proud Men, of which always are too many, the moſt manifeſt Integrity and Wiſdom will not be ſufficient to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them Truth and Juſtice.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The contempt or undervaluing of them and their Authority (which follow upon our Judgment) is of much worſe effect than that of private Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as generally Laws, publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and Sentiments, and Examples
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:47246:106"/> too ſometimes are of more uſe than pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Opinions and Examples: They being, I ſay, generally better, of more comprehenſive and certain good effect, as done by a greater and more generous Charity, with more of a publick Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and more Prudence and Wiſdom: Private Perſons, eſpecially ſtill the more Vulgar, are generally more Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and Fooliſh.</p>
                  <p>(2.) Be more ſparing in declaring thy Judgment concerning Friends. For if thy Judgment be on the good hand, it will be ſuſpected Flattery or general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Self-love. And therefore it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, when any one commends his Friend, allowed for him, nay, expected he ſhould interpoſe his excuſe, that it is ſaid by him who might be ſuſpected Partial, and more apt to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what beyond the Truth. But if thy Judgment be on the worſt ſide, thou wilt be eſteemed Ungrateful, and were it never ſo true, yet it ſhould not have been ſaid by thee; and therefore in ſuch Caſes too we ſee Men Apologize and make an Excuſe, and alledg ſome more
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:47246:106"/> than ordinary reaſon, that obligeth them to paſs ſuch a Judgment on their very Friend.</p>
                  <p>(3.) Be more ſparing in doing it of thine Enemy: the reaſon is, becauſe thy Judgment will be ſuſpected and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to proceed from Hatred and Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will; I ſay, be more ſparing and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in theſe, and ſuch like Caſes. I do not ſay, but that ſometimes there may be ſufficient reaſons to do it; but then there is more than ordinary Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to be uſed in ſuch manner as I have now Inſtanc'd, to prevent or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the hinderance of its good effect.</p>
                  <p>Nay, I adviſe rather to take occaſion to paſs thy Judgment on the good ſide here; that is, to commend him and ſpeak well of him for what thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good and commendable in him; for then thy Judgment is believed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently of better effect to thoſe who hear it for encouragement to Imitation. Thou giveſt alſo a good Example to others of thy Unprejudicedneſs, and being above and untoucht by buſie Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Hatred, Ill-will, or Revenge,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:47246:107"/> and of being ſuch a generous lover of Truth and Goodneſs, as not to conceal, but willingly take notice of, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove what is really in the Perſon lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, though thine Adverſary, it may be too altogether undeſerved and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon.</p>
                  <p>And laſtly too, By this exerciſe and uſe thou really doſt procure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm in thy ſelf this Generoſity, and Manlineſs, and Chriſtianneſs (for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more commended in Chriſtian Religion) of Temper, and ſubdueſt Selfiſhneſs and the rabble of it's Slaves, thoſe <hi>inordinate and immoderate Appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites and Paſſions,</hi> makeſt them ſneak and dare not to appear.</p>
                  <p>(4.) Be more ſparing and cautious in declaring thy Judgment concerning a Perſon generally Innocent or well Diſpoſed, but once or rarely overta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; and that becauſe it is moſt likely that he will do ſo no more, or mend without thy judging him to himſelf or others. Nor is there much danger of others imitating him in one ſingle or very rare Action, when they know he
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:47246:107"/> generally doth the contrary; (only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed if one ſhould obſerve it who knows not the Man, he may be informed that the Man was ſurprized and uſeth not ſo to do) and then what needed the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or ſhame or diſcredit that thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt him, it was unneceſſary: <hi>And no evil of Pain or Puniſhment muſt be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but where it is neceſſary for a greater good.</hi> And then it is an uſual ſign to others of ſome ill nature and Pride, that is pleaſed too much in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Faults or Infirmities; when Men are ſo ready to judg the firſt; and conſequently is of bad Example to them, and prejudicial to ones ſelf. Or if thou doſt ſee reaſon to take notice of ſuch Fault or Infirmity, let it be very ſhortly, and preſently ſeconded with a Commendation of him for his general paſt Innocency or freedom there-from; and that thou doub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt not but that he himſelf the moſt diſapproves of it, and will not readily do ſo again. All which are ſigns of freedom from any Selfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of Charity and Prudence, and conſequently the more likely to have
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:47246:108"/> good effect on the Perſon concern'd, and others too.</p>
                  <p>(5.) Be ſparing in declaring thy Judgment of wrathful and baſhful Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, either to themſelves or others. One reaſon is, becauſe the wrathful and angry Man will not and cannot bear it through Pride, and the baſhful through Shame, that is, Fear. To the wrathful Man it is at leaſt to himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual; for he'll the more juſtifie or defend himſelf, and do or be the ſame thing again out of Revenge and Pride; it will give him occaſion of wrath and attempting Miſchief; he'll <hi>turn and rent thee.</hi> I ſay, this for the moſt part (as all other Directions of this kind): For ſometimes it may be requiſite for his and others Good, firſt calmly and ſoftly (ſigns of Good-will to him by doing him good) afterwards ſhortly and ſmartly (that is, out of real Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſtill, but by ſome pain or evil to him) to paſs Judgment concerning any Principle or Action of his, let him take it how he will, and but too impatiently.</p>
                  <p>And as for the baſhful Perſon, it is
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:47246:108"/> too great a puniſhment for him; leſs would have done: And always <hi>do as little evil as thou canſt:</hi> A private Hint to him would have been ſufficient. <hi>Be not a Witneſs againſt thy Neighbour with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a cauſe, and deceive not with thy Lips,</hi> ſaith the Wiſeman, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24. 28. That is, Do not paſs nor make known thy Judgment either privately or publickly, without ſufficient reaſon.</p>
                  <p>(6.) Be ſparing in declaring thy Judgment on the worſt ſide before much Company; eſpecially Perſons whoſe Favour or good Opinion is more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, and who are in no great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Imitation.</p>
                  <p>One reaſon is, becauſe moſt-what leſs Diſcredit or Diſgrace would have ſufficed to the Mending or Correcting of the Perſon; if it had been before but one or two, either before the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon himſelf concern'd, or from whom it might have been conveyed to him. The Faults or Imperfections had need be great or frequent, and the Perſon or Perſons very confident and preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, obſtinate and conceited, and a
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:47246:109"/> danger of ſome general Infection, when they are ſo much publiſhed and made known.</p>
                  <p>(7.) Be ſparing in declaring thy Judgment on the worſt ſide before Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or Adverſaries, or ill-diſpoſed.</p>
                  <p>One reaſon is, becauſe they are, or are in danger of being prejudiced and partial in their Judgments, concerning the Perſon to whom they are ill-affected already; and thou by thy Judgment confirmeſt and increaſeſt this their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality. They are but too ready to catch at and take notice of any thing ſpoken diſadvantagiouſly, and to add to it too and aggravate it; and thou art not to give them the occaſion if there be no greater good to be had thereby, not with a leſs Inconveniency to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur'd. Thoſe too that are of an ill Temper, and apt to be Envious and Proud, will make ill uſe thereof, and gratifie and augment thoſe Vices in themſelves, and afterwards be general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemptuous and ill-affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Perſon thou diſcommendeſt. It is more ſafely done, and very profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:47246:109"/> oft-times before Perſons of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nign and generous Temper, and thoſe who are Diſcreet, who make from thence profitable Obſervation of the Cauſes the miſchievous Effects of the Defects, Infirmities, Faults and Vices of Humane Nature, to Direct, Govern, and Moderate themſelves, to Adviſe and Counſel others with Reaſon, and even the Perſon himſelf whoſe faults are noted, if it comes fairly in their way: Not to contemn or diſpiſe the Perſon in general, much leſs to hate him. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times this may be done unawares, but oft-times it proceeds from an ill will to the Perſon judged; and therefore from an intent and deſign to exaſperate and incenſe his Adverſaries againſt him more; knowing they are apt eaſily to take fire. Oft-times it comes more from Flattery, to pick Thanks and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratiate ones-ſelf with him who is ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to the Perſon judged, whom they judg they pleaſe hereby, being willing to hear of the others Faults and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, to gratifie his Hatred or Pride, or that he may have wherewithal to
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:47246:110"/> juſtifie his being ſo diſpos'd againſt him, that he might ſeem to be his Enemy with more Reaſon. If it be not thus, yet oft-times this will be ſuſpected; a Man will incur the ſuſpicion of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generous Revenge, or Hatred, or Ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, or Flattery, or at leaſt the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Imprudence.</p>
                  <p>That's the <hi>7th</hi> Rule, Be more ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in thy Judgment, 1. Concerning Superiors. 2. Friends. 3. Enemies. 4. Once or rarely Surprized. 5. To and of wrathful and baſhful Perſons. 6. Before much Company. 7. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Enemies or Ill-diſpos'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. VIII.</head>
                  <p>8. Be apt and inclin'd rather to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thy Judgment concerning others till thou art deſired; and that either by the Perſon himſelf, or others who may be much neceſſarily concern'd to know an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Perſons Qualities or Conditions; and then not to refuſe it. Some Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are, becauſe that hereby thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomeſt and uſeſt thy ſelf to Self-go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:47246:110"/> and Direction, to Act for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Ends, and by certain Rules, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly thou cauſeſt thy ſelf to refrain thy ſelf, and to be free and averſe from Buſie-bodineſs, and impertinent and profitable medling with other Mens Matters, and other bad Principles of Judgment, partly by meer diſuſe, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by attending to this Rule, and the good effects of it: Again, thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is then more likely to be true. Further, Thou ſecureſt thy ſelf alſo from ſuſpicion of Prejudice, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently thy Judgment is more heeded, and it being more likely to be true, may be of good uſe to the Perſon deſiring, and the other concerning whom it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired if known, to adviſe and forewarn them of ſome Fault or Imperfection to be reformed or get rid of, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would not have been minded or believed. Further, Thou doeſt a very good turn for, and gratifieſt him that inquires of thee. It may be alſo an occaſion of a good Turn and of a Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the other Perſon thou paſſeſt thy Judgment of, to remove ſome unjuſt
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:47246:111"/> Suſpicions or Opinions concerning him. It may be he was believed or ſuſpected worſe than he was. Thou mayſt recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie ſome Miſtakes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. IX.</head>
                  <p>9. Thou mayſt then more freely and frequently declare thy Judgment con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one to another, or to more; when thou ſeeſt them deficient in Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or Wiſdom, to take care of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and particularly when they are actually Ignorant of ſomething in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon, which may be of great concernment to them; or are deceived in their Opinion concerning him, whence ſome great Detriment or Dammage may ariſe from one to the other.</p>
                  <p>Thus for Example: If a Man knows or reaſonably ſuſpects a Man to be Falſe and Faithleſs, to be Fraudulent, or to be Poor and Inſufficient, who yet would be bargaining with, or borrowing of another, or getting ſome intereſt in his Perſon or Eſtate, of which he may be
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:47246:111"/> Ignorant; or to perſwade to ſome Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Opinions which may be childiſh, fooliſh, or hurtful; a Man may adviſe the Perſons concerned, and give them his Judgment then unasked, not out out of any Ill-will to the one; but of Good-will to and Care of the other: <hi>For a Man ought to be a Friend to every Man, and a Brother,</hi> and not permit if he can any one to be dammaged or miſchieved, and to keep him from the commiſſion of a Sin. A Man may oft-times meet with Perſons in the World who are innocent too and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, of no great prudence and fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, who are alſo raſh and precipitate, or dull and inapprehenſive, who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be eaſily impos'd upon by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and made a Prey of by them. Here it is a prudent piece of Charity to adviſe and fore-warn and to diſcover the Deſigns and Qualities of thoſe who would and do abuſe their Simplicity, and imprudent well-meaning Honeſty.</p>
                  <p>Some Reaſons of this are the ſame with the former. It is an exerciſe of
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:47246:112"/> Virtue and Prudence in our ſelves. It is an act of more than ordinary Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Perſon in danger to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to lend him thus the uſe of thine Eyes for his ſafety and good. It is a very ſeaſonable making uſe of thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; that is, it will do moſt good now, when at another time perhaps it would do none atall, or not ſo much. Here in this caſe when a Man deſires thy Opinion or Judgment, thou removeſt his Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and ſatisfieſt him perhaps, if he be Ignorant thou informeſt him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as if thou giveſt thy Judgment unask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, before thou art deſired, and where the Man is ſufficient himſelf, thou wilt do them no kindneſs, nor will they ſo much mind thee, nor thank thee for it; for it may be they have none, or not ſuch need of thy Judgment juſt then; and thou wilt be more ſuſpected too of Buſie-bodineſs or Ill-will. So alſo where thou art not deſired by one Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to give thy Judgment concerning ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her Perſon, but unasked becauſe of the Perſons Inſufficiency, out of
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:47246:112"/> Charity thou doeſt it, the effects moſt-what are very good, and if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou doeſt it, thou art no leſs prudent than charitable. And theſe are the moſt conſiderable Rules I have now thought of, for the Mannagement and Government of our ſelves in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others; which in very few words for Memory ſake, I will reckon up again.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Be ſure it be never inconſiſtent with Charity, but always done out of the proſpect of ſome good end.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. With the exacteſt truth.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Beware of all Paſſions before Judgment.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Declare not thy Judgment when thou thy ſelf art guilty. Or</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If thou doſt, firſt accuſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn thy ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. It is better and ſafer generally, not to declare thy Judgment of Perſons.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Be ſparing in judging and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thy Judgment on the worſt ſide concerning Superiors, Friends, Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Surprized, Wrathful and Baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Perſons, before much Company,
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:47246:113"/> before Enemies and Ill-diſpoſed.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Defer thy Judging much, till thou art deſired or asked.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Interpoſe it to them whom thou ſeeſt defective in their Ability or Care for themſelves. Many more by Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience may be taken notice of and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. X.</head>
                  <p>10. I have nothing more to do in this Argument now, but only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind you of the two general things I intended and aimed at in this Diſcourſe principally to recommend to you, and that is <hi>Charity and Prudence,</hi> in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that is very frequent, and takes up a very conſiderable part of our Lives. For it is very obvious and eaſie to obſerve, that a great part of our Actions of Life, are the thinking and judging, and talking and diſcourſing of other Perſons, their Qualities and Actions. The <hi>Charity</hi> is in the laſt of the ſix Particulars. The contrary
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:47246:113"/> of which I here think principally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited, which was to judg out of any <hi>nltimate</hi> Selfiſhneſs, and therefore not out of Buſi-bodineſs, Hatred, Revenge, Pride, Affectation of Superiority, Envy, Contempt, Anger, Flattery, or the like. But if this bad Principle be prohibited, than if ever Judging be permitted in any Caſe (as ſure it is) the contrary of Charity is command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; for one of thoſe Ends and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples muſt be our <hi>Prudence,</hi> is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the other five prohibited Judgments, <hi>viz.</hi> to be too prone to judg in general, to be too much inclined to judg on the worſt ſide, to judg raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to judge falſly, to be too forward in declaring our Judgments. All the Cauſes, Conſequences, Remedies and Rules I have mention'd, are but more particulary Motives and Incentives to our Charity, or Directions for our Prudence. And now therefore I hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily exhort you to the Practice of what hath been ſpoken. That you would adorn this part of your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation with the two moſt excellent
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:47246:114"/> Ornaments, not only of our Souls, but of the Divine Nature it ſelf. For our Charity and Prudence are but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle imitations of God's infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Goodneſs. How beautiful, lovely, and pleaſant a thing it is to ſee each one diſcreetly tender of his Neighbours good Name, Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Intereſt, or Concern? How lovely a thing is generous Love? And what a reverend thing is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Prudence in all our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and particularly here? What unhandſome things are Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Falſehood? How ugly and contemptible Selfiſhneſs, Hatred, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Pride, Envy, Contemptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, unguided Anger, Buſie-bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, vain Curioſity, Flattery? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, remember we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and who it is, <hi>viz.</hi> Our Maſter and Saviour Himſelf, who hath here expreſly forbidden theſe things (<hi>Judg not that ye be not judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi>) The ſame our Maſter and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:47246:114"/> ſend down His gracious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence to help us, to do what He hath taught and commanded us,</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
